<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="3.3.0" xml:id="McShane-Jerusalem-03-Intro-tei">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
 <titleStmt><title>Introduction</title><author>McShane, Kara L.</author><author>Wright, Mark J. B.</author><sponsor>The University of Rochester</sponsor>
 <sponsor>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</sponsor>
 <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
 <funder>The University of Rochester</funder>
 <funder>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</funder><respStmt><persName>Conklin, Ashley R.</persName><resp>Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2020-10" to="2020-12">Checked and corrected bibliographic references</resp><resp from="2022-01" to="2023-06">Encoded TEI</resp><resp from="2018-11" to="2023-06">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2018-11" to="2023-06">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp><resp from="2018-11" to="2023-06">Entered corrections for print edition</resp><resp from="2020-07" to="2021-07">Formatted for print edition</resp><resp from="2022-01" to="2023-06">Formatted for XML export</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Delcourt, Steffi</persName><resp from="2023-11" to="2023-11">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2020-07" to="2020-09">Checked and corrected bibliographic references</resp><resp from="2023-08" to="2023-09">Collected metadata</resp><resp from="2022-04" to="2024-06">Encoded TEI</resp><resp from="2020-07" to="2023-10">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2020-07" to="2023-10">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp><resp from="2020-07" to="2023-10">Entered corrections for print edition</resp><resp from="2022-04" to="2023-09">Formatted for XML export</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Kephart, Daniel</persName><resp from="2023-10" to="2023-10">Collected metadata</resp><resp from="2024-07" to="2024-07">Uploaded / Published Digital Edition</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Lupack, Alan</persName><resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp><resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp>Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp><resp>Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp><resp>Wrote reader report</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Norris, James</persName><resp from="2024-02" to="2024-05">Collected metadata</resp><resp from="2024-07" to="2024-07">Uploaded / Published Digital Edition</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Peck, Russell A.</persName><resp>Copyedited and proofread</resp><resp>Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp>Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp><resp>Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp><resp>Wrote reader report</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Price, Eleanor</persName><resp from="2024-05" to="2024-06">Encoded TEI</resp><resp from="2024-01" to="2024-03">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Yee, Pamela M.</persName><resp from="2020-10" to="2021-01">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2020-10" to="2021-01">Collated and entered corrections</resp><resp from="2020-10" to="2021-01">Copyedited and proofread</resp><resp from="2018-11" to="2023-10">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2018-11" to="2023-10">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp><resp from="2018-11" to="2023-10">Entered corrections for print edition</resp><resp from="2023-09" to="2023-09">Formatted for XML export</resp><resp from="2020-10" to="2021-01">Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp><resp from="2020-10" to="2021-01">Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp><resp from="2020-10" to="2021-01">Wrote reader report</resp></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Encoded in TEI in 2024</edition>
 </editionStmt>
 <publicationStmt>
 <publisher>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
 </address>
 <publisher>The Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://www.sas.rochester.edu/eng/</addrLine>
 </address>
 <publisher>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</publisher>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://teams-medieval.org/about/</addrLine>
 </address>
 <distributor>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</distributor>
 <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
 </address>
 <availability status="restricted">
 <p>Downloading shall be restricted to one copy for private use.</p>
 </availability>
    <date/>
 </publicationStmt><seriesStmt>
 <title level="s">The Middle English Text Series</title><respStmt><persName>Mario Bisciotti</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Techincal Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Mead Bowen</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Theresa Coletti</persName><orgName>University of Maryland</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Ashley R. Conklin</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Rita Copeland</persName><orgName>University of Pennsylvania</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Lisa Fagin Davis</persName><orgName>Medieval Academy of America</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Steffi Delcourt</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Margaret Dull</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Director of Metadata Strategies, Technical Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Susanna Fein</persName><orgName>Kent State University</orgName><resp>Associate Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>John Geck</persName><orgName>Memorial University of Newfoundland</orgName><resp>TEI Consultant, Technical Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Alexandra Gillespie</persName><orgName>University of Toronto</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Sue Gleason</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Techincal Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Thomas Goodmann</persName><orgName>University of Miami</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Thomas G. Hahn</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Consulting Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>David A. Lawton</persName><orgName>Washington University in St. Louis</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Michael Livingston</persName><orgName>The Citadel</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Alan Lupack</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Associate Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Andrea Noto</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Techincal Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Peter Nowak</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Technical Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Katie Papas</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Section Supervisor, The Robbins Library, Technical Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Russell A. Peck</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>General Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Caleb Prus</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Undergraduate Intern, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>David Raybin</persName><orgName>Eastern Illinois University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Eve Salisbury</persName><orgName>Western Michigan University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Anna Siebach-Larsen</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Associate Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Lynn Staley</persName><orgName>Colgate University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Jeff Suszczynski</persName><orgName>Univeristy of Rochester</orgName><resp>Web Applications Programmer, Technical Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Victoria Szabo</persName><orgName>Duke University</orgName><resp>Consulting Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>David Wallace</persName><orgName>University of Pennsylvania</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Bonnie Wheeler</persName><orgName>Southern Methodist University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Pamela M. Yee</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Assistant Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Alexander J. Zawacki</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Mellon Fellow in the Digital Humanities, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt></seriesStmt>    
 <sourceDesc>
 <biblStruct>
 <monogr><author>Unknown</author><editor>McShane, Kara L.</editor><editor>Wright, Mark J. B.</editor><title>The Destruction of Jerusalem, or Titus and Vespasian</title><imprint>
 <publisher>Medieval Institute Publications</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Kalamazoo, MI</pubPlace><date>2021</date></imprint>
 </monogr>
 </biblStruct>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
  <projectDesc>
        <p>The Middle English Texts Series offers a diverse and representative array of literary texts that medieval readers in the present-day British Isles would have encountered between the twelfth and sixteenth centuries. It is committed to making available both affordable print and open access editions to scholars, teachers, and students of the Western Middle Ages. In its digital publications, the series prioritizes a user-friendly interface and viewing options, multiple downloadable formats, enhanced searchability and filtering, and accessibility to the widest possible range of users.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>METS takes as its mission the creation of affordable editions that would pass scrutiny from the most demanding expert, yet would prove comprehensible, and even enticing, to someone who had never read Middle English before. This agenda dictates that METS publications offer not a critical edition reflecting all surviving manuscripts, and certainly not a diplomatic edition, but a best-text edition, informed by the notes and apparatus of earlier editions (where these exist), and by substantive variants from other manuscript witnesses. Transcriptions of Middle English texts are lightly modernized to ensure a smooth reading experience, while non-English texts preserve both the original language and a modern English translation in facing-page format. Each edition offers expert assistance with language and lexicon, providing glosses alongside the text(s), textual and explanatory notes, elucidation of unfamiliar contexts and traditions, and thematic and interpretive possibilities. All editions feature general introductions that set the edited text within its own time, place, and traditions, and link it to ancestor, congener, and successor materials. All publications contain comprehensive, current bibliographies of pertinent scholarship and criticism. House style is adapted from the <hi rend="italic">Chicago Manual of Style</hi>.</p><correction>
          <p>This text may include corrections made after the original edition went to press in order to correct errors and improve glosses. For a full list of editorial and typographical corrections made to this edition, please view its correction log on Github: https://github.com/mets-editions/mcshane-jerusalem/blob/main/mcshane-jerusalem-export-corrections-log.docx</p>
        </correction></editorialDecl><schemaRef url="https://metseditions.org/schema/mets-editions.xsd"/>
 </encodingDesc><profileDesc><langUsage><language ident="en">English, Modern (1500-present)</language></langUsage></profileDesc></teiHeader>
    <text><body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><anchor xml:id="McShane-Jerusalem-03-Intro"/><div type="text">
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="1">The <hi rend="italic">Destruction of Jerusalem</hi>, known also as <hi rend="italic">Titus</hi><hi rend="italic"> and Vespasian</hi>, represents one anonymous writer’s attempts to situate the city of Jerusalem as a central pivot point in history: a sacred city of God’s chosen people, the site of the execution of God’s son, and later the divine vengeance for this act upon God’s chosen people that represents God’s rejection of salvation for the Jews in favor of the Gentiles and Christians, represented by the future Roman emperors Titus and Vespasian. Like many Roman historical epics, <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> seeks to inscribe a divine, salvific meta-narrative onto human events. The poem is inspired by the historical events of 70 CE and the Jewish War undertaken by the Romans against a rebellious province, Judea. Replete with miraculous healings, cannibalism, graphic violence, and detailed accounts of siege tactics, it presents an historical romance akin to works such as <hi rend="italic">Richard Coer de Lion</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Siege of Jerusalem</hi>, or the Middle English Charlemagne romances. At over five thousand lines, <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> seeks to present an authoritative, comprehensive account of the fall of Jerusalem, drawing on a complex range of vernacular and Latin sources to do so.</p>
 <p style="body" n="1">Yet the poem’s form and content both contribute to its ongoing marginalization. This position is not helped by the opinions of the few scholars who study it: Phyllis Moe refers to the poem as “an artistic failure,” while Early English Texts Series editor J. A. Herbert observes that the poem “is intended to be octosyllabic . . . but our author cannot have had a very fine sense of rhythm.”<note target="#1" type="footnotelink">1</note> In addition to the poem’s clunky language, it amplifies the antisemitism found in works like the Middle English <hi rend="italic">Siege of Jerusalem</hi>, making the poem both difficult and troubling for contemporary readers. Indeed, <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> is usually referenced only in comparison to <hi rend="italic">Siege of Jerusalem</hi>, almost always to suggest that <hi rend="italic">Siege</hi> is comparatively the superior and more complex work. Yet, as Maija Birenbaum notes, “In its uniquely affective, participatory rendition of the fall-of-Jerusalem narrative, the poem [<hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>] engages with fourteenth-century discourses about the importance of the sacraments, specifically penance; cultural and spiritual anxieties about Jews and heretics; and fears of divine vengeance for the sins of Christendom.”<note target="#2" type="footnotelink">2</note> The poem provides a crucial, if troubling, perspective in ongoing conversations on Crusades literature, Middle English popular romance, and medieval antisemitism. With this edition, then, we hope to bring renewed scholarly attention to this overlooked work.</p>
 <p style="body" n="2">We deviate here from the title previously given to the poem by editors; that is, we have inverted Herbert’s “Titus and Vespasian, or the Destruction of Jerusalem” to call the poem simply <hi rend="italic">The Destruction of Jerusalem</hi>. This is, of course, itself an argument, and we suggest that this is a more appropriate way to designate the poem. To begin with, this title is entirely editorial; headings given to the poem in manuscripts emphasize either the place of Jerusalem or the violence against Jews, rather than the work’s Roman characters.<note target="#3" type="footnotelink">3</note> Inverting the traditionally-given title, then, brings modern practice more into keeping with medieval notions of what the poem is indeed about. It places the focus on the violence that is at the poem’s heart. Further, our title links this poem more closely to Early Modern performances and versions of the legend, suggesting the poem’s continuity both with its sources and with later adaptations of the narrative.<note target="#4" type="footnotelink">4</note></p>
 <p style="heading" n="1">The Plot</p>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="2">Like many Middle English works, <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> is episodic, and the transitions between episodes are often quite abrupt. There are two distinct versions of the poem, a short and a long version; the long version includes an extended prologue and two substantial digressions from the central plot.<note target="#5" type="footnotelink">5</note> The first, an account of the birth and early life of Pontius Pilate, appears from line 1483 to line 1622. The second, from line 4461 to line 4858, describes the life of Judas Iscariot, including his birth, abandonment, adoption, and murder of his adopted brother. Judas makes his way to Jerusalem and befriends Pilate. He unknowingly kills his father in a fight and marries his mother, who sends him to Jesus to repent of these sins when they discover that they are related. The episode then describes Judas’s eventual death by hanging himself after his betrayal of Jesus.</p>
 <p style="body" n="3">In the long version of the poem edited here, the first 910 lines serve as a lengthy prologue, retelling several key episodes in the life of Jesus familiar from the Gospels. The first describes Nicodemus’s encounter with Jesus, in which Jesus tells him about the future destruction of Jerusalem. The next episode describes Jewish officials who ask Jesus to whom their taxes should be paid; Jesus asks whose image appears on their coins. When the Jews tell them that Caesar appears on them, he advises them to pay their taxes to Caesar but render God what is owed to Him. Then, the officials challenge Jesus by bringing him a woman caught committing adultery. Jesus responds by writing in the earth and then admonishes that the one of them who is without sin should deliver her punishment, and the officials all creep away. Jesus then tells the woman to go and to keep herself from sin in the future. In the next episode, the Jews question Jesus’s authority, because they have the law from their ancestors; Jesus responds that he could destroy and raise their temple in three days, which angers the assembly. Jesus continues to defend himself against the charge of Sabbath-breaking for healing on the Sabbath. From there, the poem details events of the Passion, emphasizing an episode in which Jesus entered the courtyard of the temple and, angry at seeing trade and the exchange of coins there, turned over the tables and drove the sellers out. Because of this deed, the poem claims, those whom Jesus admonished led the group that captured Jesus and eventually put him to death.</p>
 <p style="body" n="4">After these Biblical episodes, the poem transitions to events occurring in Jerusalem after Jesus’s death. The central episode here is the martyrdom of St. James the Less, drawing heavily on the <hi rend="italic">Legenda Aurea</hi>. James, Bishop of Jerusalem, lives a holy life of preaching; indeed, he is so earnest and spends so much time in prayer that the skin on his knees becomes hard from so much time on bare stone. One Passover, the Jews admonish James to stop his preaching, but James preaches all the more, with even greater enthusiasm. Enraged, the Jews strike him with a fulling staff, and James bleeds to death in his church. From there, the poem describes nine others signs, astrological and prophetic, that occur in Jerusalem to foretell the city’s destruction. These signs continue through line 1156 of the poem.</p>
 <p style="body" n="5">Following this lengthy opening, the poem gives an account of Pontius Pilate’s treachery and abuse of power in Jerusalem. When Pilate learns that the emperor Tiberius intends to exile him from the city, he sends a messenger, Nathan, to Rome with a letter defending Pilate and recounting Jesus’s death. Nathan is blown off course en route and eventually lands in Bordeaux. In Bordeaux, we learn that the king, Vespasian, is ill, suffering from leprosy and a swarm of wasps that have lived in his nose since his birth. Nathan meets Vespasian’s son, Titus, who explains that Tiberius is dead and Nero is now emperor in Rome. Titus agrees to help Nathan reach Rome if Nathan can offer any aid to Vespasian. In response, Nathan laments that there was one who could help in Jerusalem, but that man has been killed. Nathan then retells the story of Jesus to Titus and Velosian, Vespasian’s steward. The digression on the life of Pontius Pilate falls here. After this, the plot returns to following Nathan, who completes his errand in Rome and returns to Jerusalem.</p>
 <p style="body" n="6">After Nathan departs Bordeaux, Velosian goes to the king and seeks permission to go to Jerusalem on Vespasian’s behalf. Velosian intends to seek some object that once belonged to Jesus, hoping that such an object could heal Vespasian’s condition, as well as to make sure he can recognize Pontius Pilate in case Vespasian and his forces ever find themselves attacking Pilate. In incredible pain and discomfort, Vespasian agrees, and Velosian travels to Jerusalem. Upon arrival, Velosian meets Jacob, a secret Christian living in the city, and explains Vespasian’s situation. Jacob introduces Velosian to Veronica, a woman healed by Jesus who has secretly kept a cloth bearing the image of Jesus’s face. Veronica agrees to accompany Velosian to Bordeaux, since Pilate has been persecuting both her and Jacob because Pilate suspects they are Christians. Before Velosian and Veronica depart, however, Velosian asks Jacob if any of Jesus’s torturers are still alive. Jacob explains that he sees them in the street every day and calls them together, and these torturers detail the violence they did to Jesus before his death. Velosian tells them he will tell the story everywhere he can, and once the torturers depart, he vows to bring Vespasian to Jerusalem to avenge their deeds if Vespasian regains his health.</p>
 <p style="body" n="7">Velosian and Veronica travel to Bordeaux, and upon arrival, Veronica meets Clement, a disciple of Peter’s who has fled Rome in exile. When Veronica is summoned before Vespasian, she brings Clement with her, explaining that he can speak words and perform deeds that she cannot. Clement gives a sermon to Vespasian and his court, preaching Christian doctrine. Evidently moved by this preaching, Vespasian vows that if he is healed, he will go to Jerusalem and avenge the death of Jesus. Veronica then presents the cloth to Clement, who bids Vespasian to kiss it. Vespasian is instantly healed, and he rewards Veronica and Clement with land and money. Clement warns Vespasian that he should be baptized before he leaves for Jerusalem, but Vespasian instead makes his son Titus and his men swear to accompany him. Vespasian and Titus receive leave from Nero to go to Jerusalem, leaving Clement in control of Bordeaux. They depart, with Vespasian promising to be baptized upon his successful return. They leave Bordeaux with Clement’s blessing.</p>
 <p style="body" n="8">Titus and Vespasian go first to Acre, take the city easily, and continue to Jaffa. The citizens of Jaffa do not willingly surrender, and many of them kill each other rather than submitting to Vespasian and Titus’s army. One man, Japhel, survives and joins their forces, and Vespasian gives him a place of honor both because he is related to the emperor of Rome and because he knows the geography of the area well. Citizens flee from the surrounding area, seeking shelter inside Jerusalem. A frightened Pilate summons the king of Galilee, Archilaus, to help him, and Archilaus advises Pilate to hole up inside Jerusalem’s secure walls. Vespasian’s forces put the city under siege, and Archilaus encourages Pilate to go to the city walls and challenge Vespasian, which he does. Vespasian takes offense at the challenge, telling Pilate that he will regret it and admonishing Archilaus for siding with Pilate. The fighting begins as Vespasian’s forces construct and deploy various siege weaponry. The war lasts for seven years. In the fifth year of the siege, Nero dies in Rome and Vespasian is chosen his successor. A messenger rushes to Jerusalem to bring the news to Vespasian, and Vespasian departs to be crowned. He returns as quickly as he can to the war.</p>
 <p style="body" n="9">The poem then shifts briefly to events inside Jerusalem. Within the city, Pilate accuses Jacob of helping Vespasian’s forces, and Jacob is imprisoned. When Jacob’s daughter Marie realizes her father is missing, she prays to Jesus that Jacob will be delivered, and Jesus releases him from his prison. Jacob leaves the city and eventually reaches Vespasian’s forces, where Velosian immediately recognizes him and speaks for him. Jacob is able to provide the force with valuable strategic advice, which they quickly take. Many in the city, including Josephus, an advisor to Pilate, sneak out to attack. Josephus is injured in the battle that follows, but he survives because he is secretly Christian.</p>
 <p style="body" n="10">Inside the city, resources have begun to fail, notably food, leading to mass starvation and suffering. A Christian woman named Marie and her companion Clarice heed an angel’s advice and cook and eat Marie’s deceased daughter. Pilate is horrified and forbids the people to eat their children, advising them instead to eat their gold and silver. They do so, but mass cannibalism continues in the city.</p>
 <p style="body" n="11">Jacob leaves Vespasian’s camp and goes to the city wall to investigate what is happening inside Jerusalem. He meets Josephus on the wall, and Josephus confesses his faith and describes the wretched conditions inside the city to Jacob. Josephus claims that the Jews would have surrendered already if Vespasian had been baptized, but that they will not surrender to a non-Christian. When Jacob goes back to Vespasian with his report, Josephus returns to Pilate and the assembled Jews to advise that they yield the city. Many of the Jews instead kill themselves and each other as a means to end their suffering. Those who survive bid Pilate to give up the town, claiming that they are suffering due to their sin in the persecution and death of Jesus.</p>
 <p style="body" n="12">Josephus and several companions escape the city and take shelter in a cave, but without resources, they are quickly reduced to killing and eating each other. When only Josephus and one companion remain, Josephus kills his companion in self-defense and leaves the cave, making his way to Vespasian’s forces. At first, Vespasian orders him bound, but Josephus is quickly released when the Romans discover that Josephus is Christian. Josephus then heals Titus of a serious illness, earning honor for himself among the Romans.</p>
 <p style="body" n="13">After this, the Romans take the city. Pilate pleads with Titus to preserve his position, but Vespasian’s forces show him no mercy, binding him to await punishment. Titus and his men begin to destroy the city, and in the process they find a place where the wall seems unusually thick. When they break the wall, they discover that Joseph of Arimathea, who buried Jesus and spoke against the Jews, has been walled in for the entire seven-year siege. The Romans release Joseph and show him great honor, along with other Christians found in the city. Vespasian then conducts a massive sale of the Jewish survivors, selling them thirty for a penny and encouraging the Christians to chop them open and extract the treasure that Pilate told them to eat earlier in the poem. Pilate himself is sealed alive in a barrel and sent to Viene to be imprisoned. Upon arrival, Pilate is removed from his barrel and put in prison, where he receives only water and rough bread for food except on holy days. After some time in prison, Pilate begs a guard for a paring knife and kills himself with it. His guards seal Pilate in the barrel again and toss it into the water. However, Pilate’s punishment does not end here: demons torment Pilate by tossing the barrel around, and those who pass the barrel are frightened by the shrieks and other noise. Eventually, the local clergy and people come to the shore of the water and pray, and Pilate’s barrel is secured in a hole in the rock. After this, the poem’s second major digression, on Judas Iscariot, unfolds.</p>
 <p style="body" n="14">After describing Pilate’s death, the poem then returns to Vespasian, who rewards his men for their faithfulness. Vespasian, Titus, and their army return from Jerusalem and are baptized. Vespasian confirms Clement as Pope. The last episode recounts a “miracle” that occurs when several surviving Jews return to the site of Jerusalem to rebuild the city. After two divine warnings in which red crosses appear first on the ground and then on the clothing of the Jews, the Jews return to the site for a third time and are killed when fire suddenly springs out of the ground.</p>
 <p style="heading" n="2">The Historical Siege: Josephus and the Jewish War (66–72 CE)</p>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="3">In this section we will examine some of the key contexts for our romance. We will start with the history of the event itself, then turn our attention to the historiography of the event in Josephus’s<hi rend="italic"> Jewish War</hi>; finally, we will examine the later reception of Josephus’s <hi rend="italic">Jewish War</hi>.</p>
 <p style="body" n="15">For Jews, the War in Judea was a cataclysmic event that culminated with the destruction of Herod’s expansion of the Second Temple.<note target="#6" type="footnotelink">6</note> On the other hand, for the Flavian dynasty (69–96 CE), the war provided a basis for their claims to the imperial throne after the disastrous civil discord in Rome of the so-called “year of the four Emperors,” 69 CE. Within a few decades, by the end of the first century CE, the early Christians would grow more eager to distinguish themselves from the Jewish faith and people, as figures like Saul (later Paul) of Tarsus expounded the Gospel to Gentiles. These Christians saw the destruction of the Temple as a sign of the greater validity of their faith: now Christianity had “superseded” Judaism, with a new covenant for all people.<note target="#7" type="footnotelink">7</note> This idea could quickly turn anti-Judaic, as Christian writers began to blame the people of Judea for rejecting Jesus of Nazareth as the Messiah and for responsibility for his execution at the hands of Pontius Pilate (for which the Gospel of John provides a particularly pointed example).<note target="#8" type="footnotelink">8</note></p>
 <p style="body" n="16">Looking at these three responses to the war — Jewish grief at the destruction of the Temple, Roman imperial triumph, and Christian supersessionism — it may seem hard to uncover any relatively unbiased narratives of the war. What makes this even more difficult is the fact that there is only one main ancient source for the conflict, the <hi rend="italic">Jewish War</hi> of Flavius Josephus. Josephus, a Jewish priest and one-time rebel leader who surrendered early in the war to Vespasian, wrote a history of the war in seven books within about a decade of its conclusion. It is the rare history that is, in a sense, written by a loser in the war — for example, Josephus’s grief at the fall of the city and the Temple is palpable.<note target="#9" type="footnotelink">9</note> Since Josephus did join up with Vespasian, and acted as an envoy for Titus during the siege of Jerusalem, his Jewish perspective is mixed with a Roman, Flavian one. In addition, actual Flavian monuments that provide a more propagandistic perspective remain in Rome; the Arch of Titus is one particularly famous example.</p>
 <p style="body" n="17">In the space of this introduction, we can only briefly recount the conflict’s vicissitudes.<note target="#10" type="footnotelink">10</note> Nevertheless, this will provide a historical “baseline” by which we may better evaluate the changes of later authors and romances. We will begin by discussing the central cultural importance of the Temple for ancient Judaism. Then we will examine the cultural tensions that sparked the Jewish revolt, and the outcome of the war itself, by turning to our main source, Josephus.</p>
 <p style="heading2" n="1">Rome and Jerusalem</p>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="4">In antiquity, the Temple was the center of Jewish faith, where sacrifice was carried out to God every day in the morning and afternoon. The first Temple had been constructed by Solomon sometime in the tenth century BCE and survived for roughly 400 years, before its destruction in the Babylonian sack of Jerusalem in 586 BCE, which began the Babylonian exile. After the return of the Jews to Jerusalem several decades later, when Cyrus and the Persians had conquered Babylon in turn, a new Second Temple was constructed by the end of the sixth century BCE. This structure was greatly expanded by Herod the Great in the 20s BCE as part of a building program to strengthen his hold and position in Jerusalem. Herod was viewed with suspicion by native Jews partly because he owed his power to dispensations of the Romans, as he and his father successively impressed Caesar, Antony, and then Octavian. Herod also replaced the previous, Jewish, Hasmonean dynasty that had ruled for a century, though under Roman sufferance for its last few decades. Another problem for Herod was that he was an Idumaean, a nearby people who been forcibly converted to Judaism during an expansionary period in the Hasmonean dynasty; while he had been raised Jewish, his religious commitment was viewed with skepticism by his Jewish subjects. Thus, expanding the Temple was a way for Herod to both demonstrate his political power and commitment to the Jewish faith. What remains of the Temple today is part of the massive foundational platform Herod built for his expanded Temple, now known in modern Jerusalem as the “Wailing Wall.”</p>
 <p style="body" n="18">An elite priestly caste, the Saducees, arranged sacrifice and maintained the temple complex. The complex itself was divided into several areas. Various outdoor courts were set aside for different groups — one for gentiles, one for Jewish women, one for Jewish men, one for priests. Another court, the Temple Court, was set aside for sacrificial offerings. Inside the Temple were three chambers: the <hi rend="italic">ulam</hi> (antechamber); the <hi rend="italic">hekhal</hi> (sanctuary), where the menorah, the showbread, and incense altar were located; and the Holy of Holies, where the ark of the covenant was originally placed. These last two chambers were separated from the rest of the Temple structure and access to them was highly restricted — only the high priest could enter the Holy of Holies and even then only on Yom Kippur (the day of atonement). Jews living outside Jerusalem in various parts of the Mediterranean, who could not easily attend Temple services, sent money to Jerusalem each year towards Temple upkeep, a tithe of a half shekel. Transport of the proceeds of this Temple tax to Jerusalem could be hazardous — liable to banditry or the avarice of local potentates along the way. For example, Josephus tells us that Mithridates VI Eupator once seized 800 talents of Jewish money (an enormous sum) from the island of Cos<note target="#11" type="footnotelink">11</note> in 88 BCE. Another incident occurred in 62 BCE, when the Roman governor of Syria, Flaccus, confiscated a large stash of Jewish gold bound for Jerusalem, as a defense speech by Cicero tells us.<note target="#12" type="footnotelink">12</note> Later, the Jews got a decree from Julius Caesar that the money for this tithe was protected, but after the destruction of Herod’s Temple, Vespasian redirected these proceeds to the Temple of Jupiter Optimus Maximus in Rome as the <hi rend="italic">fiscus Judaicus</hi>, or Jewish tax.</p>
 <p style="body" n="19">While it is doubtful that Titus and Vespasian intended from the outset to destroy the Temple, there is debate about whether its destruction was accidental, or if Titus and his generals decided to destroy it after the frustrations of a long siege.<note target="#13" type="footnotelink">13</note> Certainly Judaism was a tolerated faith in the Roman empire, even if individual Romans looked askance at Jewish culture and customs. Either way, the Temple has remained a potent cultural symbol (and its location a site of simmering interfaith conflict) to this day. The Jewish war functionally ended with the destruction of the Temple in 70 CE. It began there as well in 66 CE, when a young priest ordered that the daily sacrifices for the health of the Roman emperor were to cease. This was a response to Roman exaction of Temple funds and, when combined with other rising tensions in the region, sparked the war that would consume the region for the next several years.</p>
 <p style="body" n="20">The background and causes of the war are complex, and ultimately go back to the origins of the Hasmonean dynasty in the Maccabean revolt of the mid-second century BCE (famously retold in 1 and 2 Maccabees in the Old Testament, and in the context of the story of Hannukah). Put simply: certain revolutionary parties in Judea exploited increased cultural tensions between Jews and Romans to spark a revolt against the Romans, and that revolt was brutally suppressed by Vespasian and Titus. Josephus adds that civil discord between the revolutionary parties and those who wanted to maintain the status quo also debilitated the Jewish state, making it easy for the Romans to win the war.<note target="#14" type="footnotelink">14</note></p>
 <p style="body" n="21">For centuries, Judea had been a small region caught up in other empires — Persian, Seleucian, and then Roman. Given the limitations of communication and travel in antiquity, and the political changes and upheavals occurring at the imperial centers, Judea and Jerusalem did have periods of comparative independence. The most notable one was the Hasmonean dynasty of 140–37 BCE. The roots of the dynasty were found in the revolt of Judah Maccabeus in the 160s BCE.<note target="#15" type="footnotelink">15</note> As retold in 1 and 2 Maccabees and in the first book of Josephus’s <hi rend="italic">War</hi>, the Jews reacted against the attempts of the Seleucian king Antiochus IV to exert control on the region. Eventually, after years of conflict, Seleucid energies were needed elsewhere to defend their kingdom against rival powers (including Rome), and Judah’s brother Simon took power in Jerusalem as high priest and prince of Israel, founding the Hasmonean dynasty.</p>
 <p style="body" n="22">Simon and his successors began to expand aggressively, which created untold resentments between the Jews and neighboring Greeks, Samaritans, and Idumeans, and as a result the Roman general Pompey the Great was enthusiastically welcomed by non-Jews of the region when he clipped the wings of Hasmonean control. Eventually, constant infighting doomed the Hasmonean dynasty and the Idumean adventurer Herod replaced them, founding his own dynasty after successively winning the support of Caesar, Antony, and finally Octavian (the later emperor Augustus).</p>
 <p style="body" n="23">Rome’s entry onto the scene changed the political dynamics. First, it conquered and absorbed the Seleucid empire and by extension Judea. Second, in the figure of Pompey the Great, Rome adjudicated in a civil war between rival fraternal claimants to the Hasmonean throne. Herod’s rise to power was aided by his adept maneuvering between factions in the Roman civil wars. This meant, however, that Herod owed his power to, and Judea remained a part of, the Roman Empire. Herod’s own expansionist tendencies did much to exacerbate Gentile and Jewish tensions that had barely recovered from Hasmonean ambitions.</p>
 <p style="body" n="24">For the Romans, Herod fulfilled the role of client king — a local potentate who could keep his people under control and do Rome’s bidding as necessary, obviating the need for a Roman governor or military legate in the region. While Herod was a ruler of some talent, shown primarily in an enthusiastic liquidation of any potential rivals to the throne and in appointing unknowns to the high priesthood, his descendants were judged by the Romans to be unfit for rule and so in 6 CE, upon Herod’s death, Judea was formally absorbed into the Roman Empire and a procurator was appointed to rule over the Judeans.<note target="#16" type="footnotelink">16</note> A procurator was not a governor per se, but more of a bureaucratic administrator, who might have a few cohorts at his command to keep the peace but would be outranked by a legate or official Roman governor, in this case the governor of Syria, the main Roman province in the region. The most famous procurator of the Judeans was, of course, Pontius Pilate. Pilate was not a bad procurator by Roman standards, and was certainly not as antagonistic to the Jews as his successors could be, nor the craven and calculating moral monster of the <hi rend="italic">Destruction of Jerusalem</hi>.</p>
 <p style="body" n="25">The procurators and other officials sent by Rome were, as often in such cases, of varying quality. The Jews expected that they could have some outlet for complaints with the local Roman governor, or ultimately even appeal to the Emperor himself (Josephus, in fact, had just returned from such a mission when he found himself a general in Galilee). A larger issue, however, was Jerusalem’s loss of any kind of regional supremacy. Without a Herodian monarch, the center of power for the Roman officials had switched to nearby Caesarea, while Jerusalem remained a religious center of some importance, due to the presence of the Temple. With Jerusalem’s importance and power in the region diminished, there were legitimate Jewish fears that other peoples in the region, particularly the Samarians, would let vent the long simmering resentments over Hasmonean and Herodean rule. Given the fact that Roman auxiliary forces (locals drafted into military units to supplement and assist the actual Roman army) were made up of these locals and not Jews (due to an exemption for Jewish men from military service), there was plentiful opportunity for abuses both trivial and large. With a procurator like Pontius Pilate in the 30s CE, who strove to keep up good relations with the Jews, these resentments and fears of lost status could be minimized. With someone like the later procurator of the 50s CE, Gessius Florus, who cared little for Jewish opinion and was assigned by Nero primarily to acquire money for the imperial treasury, these resentments and fears flared up. Even though the legate at the time, Cestius Gallus, had tried to maintain good relationships with Jewish elites and technically outranked Florus, the latter’s remit from Nero constrained Gallus’s options to keep the peace.</p>
 <p style="body" n="26">The Romans respected Jewish monotheism as a traditional religion of some antiquity, and in return the Jews offered sacrifices to God daily on behalf of the emperor’s health. Nevertheless, most Romans found Jews to be a strange, highly insular people, and the references in Latin literature to Jews tend to be contemptuous in one way or another.<note target="#17" type="footnotelink">17</note> The emperor Nero shared this contemptuous attitude towards the Jews, and his youth (diminishing the prospect of a new ruler, short of war or assassination) seemed to rule out the viability of diplomatic missions to redress Jewish grievances. In short, by the mid-60s, many Jews in Jerusalem found themselves with diminished regional status, at the implacable mercy of the Romans, and victims of harassment and abuse by the local auxiliary forces. For some, like the revolution-minded Zealots, therefore, war and revolt may have seemed the only option. The regional elites of Jerusalem and Judea, the class that Rome relied on to keep order in the provinces, were unable to tamp down this revolutionary activity, particularly when the Zealots began assassinating their opponents.<note target="#18" type="footnotelink">18</note></p>
 <p style="heading2" n="2">The Outbreak of War</p>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="5">For these reasons, by 66 CE, the region was a tinderbox. One day, some Greeks began sacrificing birds in front of a local synagogue. Enraged by this sacrilege against Jewish custom, a priest at the Temple in Jerusalem stopped prayers and sacrifices for the emperor’s health. For this sign of loyalty to cease was a strong signal of potential revolt. Florus, who cared only for his mission of raising funds for Nero, immediately made things worse by leading a detachment of soldiers into the Temple and removing seventeen talents from it, a significant amount of money. This outrage plunged the city into reactionary unrest and mockery of the procurator (some people passed a basket around collecting money for Florus, jeering that he must be poor and that is why he stole from the Temple). In response, Florus sent in soldiers to arrest city leaders, who he had whipped and crucified. At this, Jewish rebels rose up and overwhelmed the garrison inside the city, while Agrippa II and his sister Berenice, Herodians who had tried to calm the Jews, fled to Galilee. Next, militants spread out over the region, destroying Roman symbols and terrorizing Romans and pro-Roman inhabitants. Some militants even took over the fortress of Masada. Florus fled, leaving to Cestius Gallus, the legate in Syria, the burden of restoring order.</p>
 <p style="body" n="27">Unlike Florus, Gallus maintained cordial relations with the Jerusalem elite, as any good Roman governor should have done. He expected that, with some quick retaliatory mop-up operations of rebelling militants in the area, he could arrange a cessation of hostilities and restore order. Upon arrival at Jerusalem, with Agrippa II and Berenice in tow, Gallus’s hopes were dashed, and those of Agrippa and Berenice dashed yet again — Judean militants even attacked the baggage train of Cestius’s force as they approached Jerusalem. Disappointed by his exclusion from the city and lacking supplies and forces for an extended siege, Gallus turned back towards the seat of his power at Antioch in Syria. The rebels, emboldened by their previous attack on the baggage train and on Gallus’s exclusion from Jerusalem, attacked the Roman forces in an ambush in the Beit-Horon pass. The Jews’ defeat of Gallus’s Roman force all but ensured a forceful response from Rome. Judea was now committed to war.</p>
 <p style="body" n="28">A frustrated and shamed Gallus returned to Antioch to plan for a more forceful response in the spring, sending some forces and cavalry to keep order amongst the cities of the Decapolis, a group of ten Hellenistic foundations, and in Galilee. In the meantime, the emperor Nero had lost faith in Gallus and recognized the need for new leadership to settle the issue. Nero faced a perennial problem of Roman emperors; he needed to find a general capable of battling the revolutionary Jews, but one who would not outshine the emperor and become, willingly or not, a threat to imperial power. He settled on the seasoned, capable non-entity Titus Flavius Vespasianus. Vespasian took his son Titus with him, and (like Gallus), brought Agrippa and Berenice as well, in order to make the most out of connections to the local elite. At the very least, the Romans would have expected to raze a few towns and then, based on Gallus’s experience there, to besiege Jerusalem. This would fulfill the basic policy need: when the Roman Empire was disrespected, reprisal was, if not always swift, always brutal — a way to both punish the initial transgression and to warn any other province or people thinking of rebelling against Roman rule.</p>
 <p style="body" n="29">The Jewish elite knew this well and realized that, as much as they themselves deplored the actions of the militants, a penalty would have to be paid and much suffering would ensue, as often happens in war: famine, disease, rape, pillage, sieges, and sacks. Forced into a defensive situation and dreading the arrival of a retaliatory force in the next campaign season, they appointed leading citizens to go out into the region and prepare other cities and towns for the oncoming Roman onslaught. One of these “generals” (for lack of a better term) was the future historian Josephus, who took responsibility for Galilee. Though his exact activities and motivations differ between the earlier account in <hi rend="italic">War</hi> and the later one in the <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, Josephus seems to have done his job competently, despite rivalrous intrigues against him by the notorious John of Ghiscala, who would go on to cause much misery in Jerusalem before the war was done. In fact, Josephus presents himself as Vespasian’s most tenacious opponent in the third book of the <hi rend="italic">Jewish War</hi>.</p>
 <p style="body" n="30">As Vespasian arrived, he knew he would have to be prepared for a siege at Jerusalem, with all the investment of manpower and resources that such an operation would entail. This was all the more reason to ensure the surrounding countryside was secure first, not least to avoid a repeat of the ambush of Gallus’s forces that had led to Vespasian’s appointment. Thus, Vespasian began by securing the region of Galilee, which would eventually bring him into contact with Josephus. Upon his arrival in Galilee, most of the cities and towns sent delegates immediately and allowed the placement of garrisons. Part of this was tactical, of course — it was all they could do to avoid the punishing force of the Roman army. Other towns tried to hold out, but those too, like Iotapata, fell to the Romans in the end. Nevertheless, though he was in nearly full control of Galilee by this point without the need for actual military activity, Vespasian still made sure there was minatory and retaliatory violence — Gallus’s losses in the ambush at Beit-Horon had to be avenged, after all.</p>
 <p style="body" n="31">For whatever reason the city of Iotapata was marked for especial punishment.<note target="#19" type="footnotelink">19</note> Josephus’s remit had been to prepare the cities of the region for just this eventuality. Though he had already successfully fled Iotapata, Josephus returned to the city as the Roman army approached and, perhaps hoping he could negotiate a settlement, chose to face the siege with the people of that city. Whatever else one may think of Josephus, this was a brave choice. He held out until the city fell before being captured in somewhat mysterious circumstances that would haunt his later career. Briefly brought before Vespasian, Josephus claimed that he was versed in prophecy and predicted Vespasian’s eventual accession to the Roman throne.<note target="#20" type="footnotelink">20</note> Vespasian, understandably seeing this as the rankest flattery, had Josephus put back with the other prisoners. When Josephus’s alleged prediction was ultimately proven actually prescient,<note target="#21" type="footnotelink">21</note> he was released and made part of the Flavian retinue. Josephus’s membership in the Jerusalem elite would allow him the opportunity to fulfill a similar diplomatic role as Agrippa II and Berenice had attempted for Gallus.</p>
 <p style="body" n="32">With Galilee secure, Vespasian moved further south, receiving the surrender of other towns in the region, Jerusalem excepted — though rich Jerusalemites escaped as they were able to Vespasian and his forces. With just about the entire region secure, Vespasian could bide his time, surround Jerusalem, and prepare as thoroughly as he could for a siege. However, the forces of civil discord active in both the city of Jerusalem itself, and in the larger Roman world, were ready to completely change the character of the war.</p>
 <p style="heading2" n="3">The Next Phase: Civil Discord in Rome and Jerusalem</p>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="6">While Vespasian was reestablishing Roman authority in the province of Judea, the center of Roman power was in upheaval, culminating in the chaos of the so-called “year of the four Emperors,” 69 CE. In 68 CE, Julius Vindex, the governor of Gaul, had revolted against Nero, supported by Galba, the nearby governor of Hispania Terraconensis, one of the Roman provinces in Spain. Though Vindex’s revolt ultimately failed, enough of the military and civil authorities in Rome had tired of Nero’s reign, with its pretentions to artistry and the bloodletting that followed the exposure of the conspiracy of Piso in 65 CE. Tried and condemned <hi rend="italic">in absentia</hi>, Nero committed suicide and Galba took the throne. Galba was overthrown in turn by the forces of Otho, who had been frustrated by Galba’s choice of heir. In the meantime, Vitellius declared for the throne in Germania. Defeated in an engagement with Vitellius’s forces at Bedriacum, Otho committed suicide rather than prolong a hopeless conflict. The senate confirmed Vitellius as emperor, though his reign began with ill omens.</p>
 <p style="body" n="33">At this point, the legions in Egypt declared for Vespasian, along with the legions in Syria and Vespasian’s own in Judea. The governor of Syria, Gaius Lucius Mucianus, also supported Vespasian. Emboldened by their support, Vespasian left the command of the Jewish war to his elder son Titus,<note target="#22" type="footnotelink">22</note> and left for Egypt to take command of the legions there. Control of Egypt gave Vespasian a distinct advantage, both because of the province’s wealth and because it was the most important grain supplier for Rome. His position was further strengthened when the legions on the Danube also declared for him. Marcus Antonius Primus led these legions in an invasion of Italy, defeating Vitellius’s forces at the second battle of Bedriacum. An increasingly desperate Vitellius was soon caught and killed, and Vespasian’s forces took the city, though Vespasian himself remained in Egypt. On December 21, 69 CE the Senate declared Vespasian the new Emperor, the fourth and final man to ascend to the throne that fateful year.</p>
 <p style="body" n="34">Back in Judea, Titus continued to prepare for the eventual siege of Jerusalem. Inside the city itself, various factions struggled for power, and the arrival of John of Ghiscala, fleeing Vespasian’s military operations in Galilee that resulted in Josephus’s capture, made matters inside the city worse. Various rival factions were packed into the city, which was nominally controlled by the Judean Free Government led by the priest Ananus ben Ananus. It was under their authority that Josephus had gone out to secure Galilee. When John of Ghiscala arrived in Jerusalem, he led the Zealots in taking control of large parts of the city, began fighting with the Judean Free Government, and executed any who advocated surrender to the Romans. The Zealots next lured a force of 20,000 Idumaeans into the city with a false message that the Judaean Free Government had already reached terms of surrender with Rome. The Zealots and Idumaeans attacked the forces of the Judean Free Government, killing Ananus ben Ananus, countless civilians,<note target="#23" type="footnotelink">23</note> and seizing the Temple. John later tricked and killed the original leader of the Zealots and began a despotic rule of the city. In response, the remnants of the Free Government invited the rebel warlord Simon bar Giora into the city. Simon had led the forces that defeated Gallus earlier in the conflict, but the Free Government still distrusted Simon and expelled him from Jerusalem. Simon fled to Masada, but eventually left that fortress too, in order to engage in banditry around Idumaea, before coming to Jerusalem once more. Simon and John’s respective forces now began a bitter civil war, only joining together when it became clear that the Roman army now led by Titus were investing for a long siege.</p>
 <p style="body" n="35">All of this was terrible enough for the poor civilians still trapped in the city (most of the wealthy elite would have fled much earlier in the conflict). The Zealots proceeded to make things far worse by burning the food supplies in the city to further induce everyone to fight against the Romans rather than surrender. As the siege began in earnest, there were probably about one million people, by Josephus’s estimate, still within the city walls.</p>
 <p style="heading2" n="4">The Fall of Jerusalem and the End of the War</p>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="7">By the summer of 70 CE, the siege had been going on for seven months. The suffering inside was ineffably terrible. Titus finally breached the city, aided by the collapse of several walls. The forces of Simon held the upper city, while John and his Zealots occupied the Temple. In July, Titus finally breached the third wall, which had been put up before the siege had begun and was the weakest of all. Though it is debated whether the destruction of the Temple was intended by the Romans or not, it burned to the ground on July 29–30, 70 CE, with monumental consequences for the Jewish and Christian faiths. The city was put to the torch, and Simon and John were captured. Both were marched in the triumph back in Rome, along with treasures looted from the Temple and city, like the Menorah. But while John was sentenced to life imprisonment, Simon was executed at the climax of the triumph.<note target="#24" type="footnotelink">24</note></p>
 <p style="body" n="36">Even though the Flavians, imperial father Vespasian, and his general son Titus celebrated a triumph after the fall of Jerusalem, the rebellion was not fully stamped out — pockets of resistance remained at Herodium and Machaerus. Finally, there were the forces still at the well-placed fortress of Masada, strategically placed atop a plateau. These rebels held out against the Roman forces until 72 CE. Determined to stamp out every vestige of the revolt, the Romans, now led by Lucius Flavius Silva, built a circumvallation (or enclosing wall) around the plateau to prevent any supplies from getting in or people from getting out. Next, they transported vast amounts of earth in order to construct a siege ramp up to the redoubt itself. When they finally broke through, the Romans found that nearly all of the inhabitants had killed themselves. The remains of the Roman siege works can still be seen at Masada today. This was the bitter end to the first Jewish War.</p>
 <p style="body" n="37">In the aftermath, Vespasian instituted the <hi rend="italic">fiscus Judaicus</hi>, a tax upon Jews which essentially redirected the half-shekel tithe to the Temple of Jupiter Optimus Maximus in Rome. He also ordered the Temple of Onias in Egypt to be destroyed, lest that become another center of insurrection. There would be two other major Jewish revolts in the Roman empire. In 117 CE, the Kitos war enflamed Jewish communities across the Eastern Mediterranean for two years before its eventual repression. Finally, in 132 CE, a revolt erupted in Judea led by Simon bar Kokhba, which was also suppressed. Afterwards, the emperor Hadrian built a Roman colony, Aelia Capitolina, on the site of the ruins of Jerusalem. Aelia Capitolina remained the name of the site until the seventh century CE and survives as the Arabic name for Jerusalem (<hi rend="italic">Iliyā</hi>).</p>
 <p style="heading" n="3">Josephus and the <hi rend="italic">Jewish War</hi></p>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="8">The Jewish War (66–72 CE) is the rare ancient conflict where a participant wrote an account of the event afterwards. Josephus thus joins a group of ancient historians that includes Thucydides (a clear and obvious model in many ways for Josephus) and Julius Caesar. Josephus’s text was written in Greek<note target="#25" type="footnotelink">25</note> and eventually translated into Latin (perhaps by Cassiodorus) and adapted into Latin by later writers, in particular the author called Pseudo-Hegesippus. In this section we will consider the life of Josephus, his corpus of works, and their transmission into later Latin translations and adaptations.</p>
 <p style="heading2" n="5">Life of Josephus</p>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="9">What we can know of Josephus’s life comes from those parts of the <hi rend="italic">War</hi> where he is a participant in the action (first as a leader in the siege of Jotapata, later as a prisoner-turned-advisor in the camp of the Flavians). Late in his life, presumably safely ensconced in Rome on the outer fringes of the new dynasty, Josephus composed a text appended to the <hi rend="italic">Antiquities</hi> which scholars call the <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> of Josephus. Rather than an autobiography in our sense, it is really an <hi rend="italic">apologia</hi> against the calumnies of another participant in the war, whose own writings are no longer extant, as well as rather revised account of Josephus’s actions during the revolt from 66–72 CE. Oftentimes, when Josephus describes an event in the <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> which he had earlier written about in the <hi rend="italic">Wars</hi>, the account in the <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> is markedly different from his earlier work. This is not a case of better research or a more detached approach to the conflict years removed, but rather the result of different goals and audiences for the two texts. Nevertheless, these divergences have vexed scholars over the years, especially when trying to put together a convincing account of the early stages of Vespasian’s campaigns, much less the life of the author of our main surviving historical account of the conflict.</p>
 <p style="body" n="38">What we can confidently say about Josephus is that he was born around 37 CE, and was descended from a priestly family on his father Matthias’s side and from the Hasmonean dynasty on his aristocratic mother’s side. Such parentage and noble lineage ensured a wealthy and comfortable upbringing for Josephus and his elder brother, named Matthias after their father. In the <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> he describes a typical elite upbringing, and rather too schematically limns his education in the major “schools” of Jewish thought in the first century CE — the Saduccees, the Pharisees and the Essenes.</p>
 <p style="body" n="39">It is worthwhile to pause for a moment to outline these three schools, both for their importance to ancient Jewish culture (Saduccees) and later Jewish, rabbinical culture (arising out of the Pharisees), and because membership in the sects tended to reflect class distinctions.<note target="#26" type="footnotelink">26</note> The Saduccees were primarily composed of the priestly elite and handled the maintenance and sacrifice at the Temple. They kept firmly to the Mosaic law or “written Torah” and eschewed the eschatological beliefs of the other sects. They also tended to be more in favor of Hellenization, and those trying to make peace with Rome would largely be of this group. The Pharisees for their part resisted Hellenization, tended to be of non-elites (Josephus reports they enjoyed broad lower class support),<note target="#27" type="footnotelink">27</note> and emphasized the oral Torah — laws and interpretations — over the written one.<note target="#28" type="footnotelink">28</note> Members of this sect would tend to want to resist Roman power. With the fall of the Second Temple, Rabbinical Judaism would evolve out of the Pharisaic sect. The last and smallest group, the Essenes, were a more eschatological, communitarian group. They lived apart from others, focusing more on purity than even other Jewish sects. It would not be too far off the mark to call these communities “monastic” in character, or at least monastic <hi rend="italic">avant la lettre</hi>, with their commitments to asceticism and (for priests) celibacy. The famous “Dead Sea Scrolls” were produced by Essenes.</p>
 <p style="body" n="40">Josephus’s first major role in adulthood was membership in an embassy to the emperor Nero, to argue for the release of twelve Jewish priests. While he was in Rome, events in Jerusalem had spiraled out of control. Almost as soon as he returned to Judea, Josephus found himself as governor of Galilee, responsible for its defensive preparations for the expected retaliatory action by the Romans. Although we cannot be sure, given how Josephus changes his account between <hi rend="italic">War</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, he may have also been sent by the elites in Jerusalem to feel out sentiment in Galilee, to see if a large-scale conflict with Rome could yet be avoided and a few guilty parties turned over for punishment — for Rome could not let the successful ambush of a legion go unrevenged.</p>
 <p style="body" n="41">While in Galilee, Josephus successfully fortified major settlements and cities in the region in preparation for the expected Roman retaliation. In both <hi rend="italic">War</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, Josephus describes his wrangling with John of Gischala for control of Galilee.<note target="#29" type="footnotelink">29</note> Their contest is left unresolved, even if Josephus gets the last laugh in his work with his vicious and caustic characterization of John, who becomes one of the leading villains in Josephus’s <hi rend="italic">Jewish War</hi>. While Josephus would leave Galilee in Roman custody, John would later make his way to Jerusalem to become a pox upon the city and its population, especially in his murderous rivalry with Simon Bar Giora, who emerges as the other lead antagonist in Josephus’s account.</p>
 <p style="body" n="42">The downfall of Jotapata was but a detour in the inexorable march of Vespasian’s legions across Galilee. As the city fell, Josephus found himself in a cave with forty other survivors. These holdouts rejected Roman calls for surrender and Josephus suggested a method of collective suicide by counting out amongst the forty lots, where the person who took the first lot would be killed by the one who chose the second. Josephus keeps this account suitably vague (he would have to, since he survived), but somehow Josephus ended up as one of the last two alive and convinced his fellow survivor to just forget about the whole thing. Leaving the cave and the bodies behind, Josephus became a Roman prisoner.<note target="#30" type="footnotelink">30</note> He cannily prophesized (suddenly in possession of a heretofore unmentioned gift of divination) Vespasian’s eventual accession to the throne, which later led to his release and elevation amongst the non-military coterie in the Flavian camp. He would prove most useful as an ambassador to the Jews of Rome, though his efforts (as in the romance) were in vain.</p>
 <p style="body" n="43">After the war, Josephus went back to Rome with his new patrons. He seems to have been present at the Flavians’ triumphal parade; in fact, he provides us with the fullest account of a Roman triumph we possess.<note target="#31" type="footnotelink">31</note> He received lands around Jerusalem from the Flavians and resided in one of their domiciles in Rome (likely one owned earlier by Vespasian). He composed all of his extant works during this Roman retirement. Especially for his later works, he benefitted from contact with several leading personages in Rome and boasted of Titus’s personal approval of the <hi rend="italic">War</hi>.<note target="#32" type="footnotelink">32</note> Nevertheless, it would seem that he was on the fringes of Flavian patronage.<note target="#33" type="footnotelink">33</note> He probably died around 100 CE.</p>
 <p style="body" n="44">As Steve Mason asserts, Josephus is not a sure guide to reconstructing the events of the <hi rend="italic">Jewish War</hi>. Nevertheless, he is our only substantial guide, sometimes assisted by archaeology.<note target="#34" type="footnotelink">34</note> However, Josephus is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> a historian in our modern sense of academic history. History, in antiquity, was a branch of rhetoric. While writers self-professedly strove to present the truth, much leeway was given to the individual writer of history in filling in the picture, according to the principle of <hi rend="italic">to eikos</hi> or “what is probable.” Josephus, first and foremost, is a literary artist, one whose art involved commemorating the past. Like our romance, Josephus sees the fate of the Temple and Jerusalem as an act of divine vengeance. However, unlike our romance, Josephus attributes this to the civil discord plaguing the city, especially the battles between Simon and John, rather than the execution of Jesus.<note target="#35" type="footnotelink">35</note> But like our romance, Josephus sees the Roman army led by Vespasian and Titus as the instrument of God’s will.<note target="#36" type="footnotelink">36</note></p>
 <p style="heading2" n="6">The Corpus and its Transmission</p>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="10">We possess four works of Josephus, all in Greek. The cultural polemics of <hi rend="italic">Against Apion</hi>, where Josephus defends the value of Jewish culture against a Hellenic detractor, will not concern us here. Most important for our purposes is the <hi rend="italic">Jewish War</hi>, a text in seven books that was likely started soon after the war’s effective conclusion (i.e., after the destruction of the Temple in 70 CE, but before the fall of Masada in 72 CE) and finished by the end of the 70s CE. This text starts from the origins of the Hasmonean dynasty in the second century BCE and concludes with the fall of Masada in 72 CE. The twenty books of <hi rend="italic">Jewish Antiquities</hi> trace Jewish history from Adam and Eve to the outbreak of the Jewish War (therefore, here too there is overlap and variation with the narrative in <hi rend="italic">War</hi>). The <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> of Josephus was apparently conceived as an appendix to this later work. Both the <hi rend="italic">Antiquities</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> date to the 90s CE.</p>
 <p style="body" n="45">As with most surviving works of Greco-Roman antiquity, we owe the preservation of Josephus’s text to the hard work of Christians in Late Antiquity and the Middle Ages.<note target="#37" type="footnotelink">37</note> There is also a Hebrew transmission, the <hi rend="italic">Sefer Yosippon</hi>.<note target="#38" type="footnotelink">38</note> The Greek text would have been preserved in the Eastern part of the Roman Empire (what modern historians call the Byzantine Empire, which outlasted the empire in the west for nearly a thousand years). The seven main witnesses to the Greek text of <hi rend="italic">War</hi> are from the eleventh century CE — which means there is still another millennium of transmission between our earliest extant texts and Josephus himself, for which we have no testimonia or evidence.<note target="#39" type="footnotelink">39</note> Latin translations and adaptations were made in Late Antiquity. A passage from Cassiodorus’s <hi rend="italic">Institutions of Divine and Secular Learning</hi> tells us that the scholar and statesman had had the <hi rend="italic">Antiquities</hi> of Josephus translated by monks at his monastery Vivarium, while ascribing a translation of the <hi rend="italic">War</hi> alternately to Jerome, Ambrose, or Rufinus.<note target="#40" type="footnotelink">40</note> There is nothing in their surviving works or testimonia that suggest Ambrose or Jerome ever attempted a translation of the <hi rend="italic">Jewish War</hi> themselves,<note target="#41" type="footnotelink">41</note> and the earliest records of attribution to Rufinus date to the fifteenth century. As Cassiodorus is writing in the sixth century CE and refers to earlier translations of the <hi rend="italic">War</hi>, it would seem the Latin translation would date to the fourth or fifth century CE (300s–400s), though absent any other information beyond the mere existence of the text and the lone testimonium from Cassiodorus, this must remain a guess.</p>
 <p style="body" n="46">In late antiquity the most notable adaptation was by Pseudo-Hegesippus, a text that seems to date from the fourth century (300s) CE, usually called <hi rend="italic">De Excidio Urbis Hierosolymitanae </hi>(<hi rend="italic">On the Destruction of the City of Jerusalem</hi>), in five books, reduced from the original seven of Josephus.<note target="#42" type="footnotelink">42</note> A somewhat compressed account of the war, it mixes elements of Josephus’s <hi rend="italic">Jewish War</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Jewish Antiquities</hi> with Christian material. The author generally follows the thread of Josephus’s account, while explicitly figuring the destruction of the city and the Temple as divine retribution for the death of Christ, rather than Josephus’s emphasis on God’s anger at Jewish discord. Because of this shared sense of God’s divine anger, it is not too difficult for an author like Pseudo-Hegesippus and later Christians to use Josephus’s narrative for their own Christian ends.</p>
 <p style="body" n="47">One factor that allowed the text of Pseudo-Hegesippus to endure is the fact that it was often ascribed to Josephus in antiquity. By the ninth century it had been (mistakenly) identified with the second-century CE Greek Christian apologist Hegesippus (hence the modern addition of Pseudo). Claiming that a text was written by an established famous author was one way to help it find an audience.<note target="#43" type="footnotelink">43</note> However, its association/confusion with Josephus’s original was also the source of its authority on the subject for centuries.<note target="#44" type="footnotelink">44</note> Thus, when it comes to deducing the source of different details of the war in texts like <hi rend="italic">The Siege of Jerusalem </hi>or our <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>, it can be very difficult to determine whether it is derived from the Latin translation of Josephus’s original or Pseudo-Hegesippus. It is likely that the author of <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> encountered Josephus through the Latin translation mentioned by Cassiodorus, Ps.-Hegessipus, or more probably a mixture of both. Though work on both traditions is limited, there is hope that more work will be done to expound these neglected aspects of Josephus’s reception.<note target="#45" type="footnotelink">45</note></p>
 <p style="heading" n="4"><hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> in the Middle Ages: The Vengeance of Our Lord Tradition</p>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="11">Though <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> has its ultimate origins in the writings of Josephus, Eusebius, and Pseudo-Hegesippus, accounts such as the one in <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> were increasingly common from the twelfth century onward, with a proliferation of similar tales across genres and languages in the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries.<note target="#46" type="footnotelink">46</note> The Old and Middle French prose <hi rend="italic">Vengeance de Nostre-Seigneur</hi> exists in over forty-five manuscripts, and the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries saw over twenty-three editions.<note target="#47" type="footnotelink">47</note> Notably, this version as well as the poetic <hi rend="italic">Venjance de Nostre Seigneur</hi> lack the episode about Judas, the account of Pontius Pilate’s birth, and the closing episode in which the Jews return to the site of Jerusalem.<note target="#48" type="footnotelink">48</note></p>
 <p style="body" n="48"><hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> weaves together a vast array of sources, the majority of them Latin. The most frequently used include the <hi rend="italic">Vindicta Salvatoris</hi>, dated to around 700 CE; Jacobus de Voragine’s incredibly popular <hi rend="italic">Legenda Aurea</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Golden Legend</hi>, a thirteenth-century compendium of saints’ lives; and the <hi rend="italic">Gospel of Nicodemus</hi>, a noncanonical account of the events in Jerusalem after the death of Jesus.<note target="#49" type="footnotelink">49</note> The four Gospels themselves, as well as the Book of Acts, provide much of the remainder of the poem’s source material.</p>
 <p style="body" n="49">Four versions of this narrative exist in Middle English: the short and long versions of <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>, the alliterative <hi rend="italic">Siege of </hi><hi rend="italic">Jerusalem</hi>, and Roger d’Argenteuil’s <hi rend="italic">Bible en françois</hi>.<note target="#50" type="footnotelink">50</note> The best known of these, the alliterative <hi rend="italic">Siege</hi>, shares some key source texts with <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>, though it is roughly a third of its length. As Adrienne Williams Boyarin notes, besides their similar subject matter, the poems share very little in common.<note target="#51" type="footnotelink">51</note> Nonetheless, as <hi rend="italic">Siege</hi> is a more familiar text for many readers, it may be helpful to address some of the crucial differences between these versions here.</p>
 <p style="body" n="50">Perhaps the most notable difference between <hi rend="italic">Siege</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> is how <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> reinforces binaries that <hi rend="italic">Siege</hi> selectively blurs, especially around each poem’s treatment of its Jewish characters. Boyarin notes that <hi rend="italic">Siege</hi> condemns Jews at many points in the text while expressing sympathy for their suffering at other moments.<note target="#52" type="footnotelink">52</note> In contrast, <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> Christianizes any character meant to be seen as virtuous — notably Jacob, Josephus, and Veronica — while categorizing all the poem’s villains as Jewish, including Pontius Pilate and Herod. Titus and Vespasian themselves are the only characters who complicate this binary: they espouse Christianity and are seen as God’s agents in enacting revenge, but they remain unbaptized until the end of the poem.<note target="#53" type="footnotelink">53</note> Likewise, <hi rend="italic">Siege</hi> contains far less opening apparatus designed to praise Jesus and vilify the Jews. <hi rend="italic">Siege</hi> tends to renarrate Christian doctrine more briefly, whereas the telling and retelling of key narratives is central to <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>: the poem contains multiple references to the disciples speaking in tongues from the Book of Acts, as well as considerably expanding Clement’s preaching to Vespasian.</p>
 <p style="body" n="51">On the whole, then, <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> is invested in reinforcing Christian religious structures, which partially explains the poem’s preoccupation with Vespasian’s deferred baptism. As one who has not been baptized, Vespasian remains a “Saracen” until after Jerusalem has been defeated, and the Jews of the city repeatedly refer to him as such.<note target="#54" type="footnotelink">54</note> Belief in Jesus may effect miraculous healing in <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>, but only the sacraments confer Christian status. As Munro notes, the poem’s closing material — in which Vespasian honors the Christians who endured in Jerusalem, confirms Clement’s status as Pope, and constructs Christian churches — seems to be unique to <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>.<note target="#55" type="footnotelink">55</note> These moments align the poem especially strongly with the Middle English romance tradition; indeed, these acts, especially the establishment of churches, appear in a range of romances, transforming Vespasian from Roman emperor to romance hero.<note target="#56" type="footnotelink">56</note> Like Gowther or Havelok, Vespasian returns home to live a religiously and politically virtuous life; Christian dominance is established, his faithful men are rewarded with lands and wealth, and he lives out his life in Rome before leaving his status as emperor to his son Titus. Vespasian’s deeds make <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> a champion of religious orthodoxy at a moment when English poetry seems particularly concerned with such orthodoxy.<note target="#57" type="footnotelink">57</note> From its preoccupation with baptism to its detailed attention to the vernicle as a relic to its ending confirmation of Clement’s papacy, <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> promotes institutional orthodoxy throughout.</p>
 <p style="heading" n="5">Cannibalism Historical and Literary</p>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="12"><hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>’s story of Maria’s cannibalism of her child, familiar to readers of <hi rend="italic">Siege</hi>, originates in Josephus, where it is the culmination of the horrors of Titus’s siege that Josephus describes in book 6.<note target="#58" type="footnotelink">58</note> As with other historians in antiquity, Josephus resorts to a number of stock episodes and scenes to flesh out his description of the siege, including cannibalism, but no other surviving ancient historian goes into the kind of horrifying detail that Josephus does in this episode. While Josephus was present outside the city during the siege, he would not have been privy to precise information about what was happening in the city, though he might have had opportunities after the war’s conclusion to interview survivors. The cannibalism episode is gruesome enough that Josephus even highlights it as a report that reached the Roman camp and disgusted Titus himself, a detail that <hi rend="italic">Siege</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> do not include.<note target="#59" type="footnotelink">59</note></p>
 <p style="body" n="52">Cannibalism has a greater cultural force in medieval than in ancient literature.<note target="#60" type="footnotelink">60</note> The ancient Greeks and Romans typically discussed cannibalism in two distinct contexts.<note target="#61" type="footnotelink">61</note> The first was as an extreme marker of cultural difference. Several ancient ethnographies of areas in and around ancient Scythia (roughly modern Eastern Europe and northern Iran) mention a tribe called the Androphagoi<note target="#62" type="footnotelink">62</note> or Anthropophagi,<note target="#63" type="footnotelink">63</note> about whom not much more is known than their descriptive tribal name, Greek for “man-eaters.” Herodotus also tells of some peoples (the Issedones and the Indians) who consume the flesh of their dead relatives,<note target="#64" type="footnotelink">64</note> though this is presented as a specific funerary cultural practice, as opposed to a general gastronomic practice for the Androphagoi, as their name would indicate.</p>
 <p style="body" n="53">The more common context for cannibalism in ancient sources is during the deprivations of siege warfare, as in Josephus’s infamous account, and by extension his many imitators, from Pseudo-Hegesippus and the <hi rend="italic">Sefer Yosippon</hi>, through the <hi rend="italic">Vengeance</hi> tradition, down to <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>. Thucydides, writing in the late fifth and early fourth centuries BCE, is our earliest surviving example of cannibalism during a siege. In his description of the siege of Potidea (which finally fell in 429 BCE) during the Peloponnesian war, Thucydides tells how the people in the city, after their grain supplies had given out, were desperate enough to eat their fellow citizens.<note target="#65" type="footnotelink">65</note> Such is the typical cannibalism in siege scene — driven by the deprivations of a protracted military operation, men inevitably are driven to extremes: war, as Thucydides tells us, is a harsh teacher.<note target="#66" type="footnotelink">66</note> There are accounts of cannibalism that feature in three other sieges: Scipio Aemilianus’s siege of Numantia in 133 BCE;<note target="#67" type="footnotelink">67</note> Sulla’s siege of Athens in 87–86 BCE, during the Mithridatic wars;<note target="#68" type="footnotelink">68</note> and Gnaeus Pompey’s siege of Calagurris in 72 BCE.<note target="#69" type="footnotelink">69</note> Plutarch’s <hi rend="italic">Lucullus</hi> provides a slight twist on the siege theme. In this case, Mithridates VI Eupator, King of Pontus, is besieging the city of Cyzicus. The Roman general Lucius Licinius Lucullus successfully cuts off Mithridates’s supply lines to the point where the conditions in his own camp become worse than those of the besieged, even as his own advisors attempt to deceive him. Soon enough Mithridates discovers the truth, which includes cannibalism on the part of his soldiers.<note target="#70" type="footnotelink">70</note> In all these cases, the emphasis is on the horror of an extended siege and the gruesomeness of this grim act, and the stories from the siege of Numantia, fragmentary as they are, remain the most chilling outside of Josephus. Like us, the ancients regarded cannibalism with, at minimum, strong distaste.<note target="#71" type="footnotelink">71</note></p>
 <p style="body" n="54">While most of these references are brief, with minimum condemnation or exculpation, two ancient accounts stand out. First, of course, is Josephus’s account of Maria and her child, which we discuss below. About a century earlier, Julius Caesar, in his account of his wars in Gaul, describes a speech of an especially fierce Gaul named Critognatus, during the climactic siege of Alesia that finally broke the revolt of Vercengetorix:</p>
 <quote>Quid ergo mei consili est? Facere, quod nostri maiores nequaquam pari bello Cimbrorum Teutonumque fecerunt; qui in oppida compulsi ac simili inopia subacti eorum corporibus qui aetate ad bellum inutiles videbantur vitam toleraverunt neque se hostibus tradiderunt.<note target="#72" type="footnotelink">72</note></quote>
 <quote>[What, therefore, is my plan? To do that which our ancestors did in the war with the Cimbri and Teutones, one that is utterly unequal to this war: men who locked themselves away in their towns and compelled by a similar want of resources nourished themselves with the bodies of those who seemed, because of their age, useless towards the war effort — nor did they hand themselves over to the enemy.]</quote>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="13">Caesar’s prefatory remarks emphasize the “singular and nefarious cruelty” (<hi rend="italic">propter eius singularem et nefariam crudelitatem</hi>, 7.77.2) of the speech — it is in fact the entire reason Caesar records it (all the more notable because it is one of the rare speeches in direct discourse in all of Caesar’s extant writings). Like the other examples, this is contextualized in a siege; like the Numantines earlier or the Usipi later, the weaker are to be consumed first to support the strong. For Caesar’s immediate purposes, this allows him to continue his characterization of the Gauls as “barbarians” and use it to justify his conquests in the region.<note target="#73" type="footnotelink">73</note> It is also an especially memorable summation of a key antithesis in <hi rend="italic">The Gallic War</hi>, book 7 between <hi rend="italic">libertas</hi> (freedom) and <hi rend="italic">servitus</hi> (servitude) — so repulsive is the latter to the Gauls that they would turn to cannibalism before surrender, as Critognatus proposes.</p>
 <p style="body" n="55">While Caesar’s is the most memorable extant passage concerning cannibalism in Latin, it is Josephus’s infamous account in the <hi rend="italic">Jewish War</hi> that really captured the medieval imagination.<note target="#74" type="footnotelink">74</note> While these authors were writing for either primarily a Greek audience, or a Roman one,<note target="#75" type="footnotelink">75</note> Josephus, as a Hellenized Jewish resident in Rome, seems to have intended his work to be read by all three of these possible audiences: Roman, Greek, and Jewish.<note target="#76" type="footnotelink">76</note> As Honora Chapman demonstrates in her reading of Maria’s episode, Josephus draws upon both the Hellenic cultural tradition (e.g. Thucydides) and Hebrew scripture in rendering this episode.<note target="#77" type="footnotelink">77</note> For all its horror, then, this episode provides a stimulating locus to see how Josephus negotiates these competing cultural traditions. As such, it also makes a good text to see how these cultural traditions are reshaped in the Latin translations, the <hi rend="italic">Vengeance</hi> tradition, and <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>.</p>
 <p style="body" n="56">Given Josephus’s use of Thucydides as a model,<note target="#78" type="footnotelink">78</note> it is likely that Josephus was familiar with the ancient historian’s account of the siege of Potidea, and certainly with the horrors of more recent sieges like Sulla’s siege of Athens, or Scipio Aemilianus’s siege of Numantia. For Greco-Roman historians, bare events (e.g. a siege, a pitched battle) were elaborated by writers of history to provide an entertaining and didactic read for their audience. Cannibalism was a stock resource for this kind of elaboration, but generally not on the scale of Josephus’s narrative in <hi rend="italic">Jewish War</hi>, book 6.</p>
 <p style="body" n="57">To elaborate this episode, Josephus draws upon Jewish tradition, where not only cannibalism but specifically that of a mother eating her own children frequently figures as part of God’s punishment of the Israelites for their failure to keep with Jewish law. Two representative examples come from Leviticus 26:28–29:</p>
 <quote>I will also go against you with opposite fury, and I will chastise you with seven plagues for your sins, so that you shall eat the flesh of your sons and of your daughters.</quote>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="14">And Jeremias 19:9, where the context is specifically a city under siege:</p>
 <quote>And I will feed them with the flesh of their sons, and with the flesh of their daughters: and they shall eat every one the flesh of his friend in the siege, and in the distress wherewith their enemies, and they that seek their lives shall straiten them.</quote>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="15">These examples are in the context of warnings from God for Jews to keep within the law.<note target="#79" type="footnotelink">79</note> There is one specific case mentioned at 4 Kings 6:28, again in the context of a siege. Here, Samaria is being besieged by King Ben-hadad of Syria, and a woman complains to the King of Israel:</p>
 <quote>And the king said to her: “What aileth thee?” And she answered: “This woman said to me: ‘Give thy son, that we may eat him today, and we will eat my son tomorrow.’ So we boiled my son, and ate him. And I said to her on the next day: ‘Give thy son that we may eat him.’ And she hath hid her son.” When the king heard this, he rent his garments.</quote>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="16">Beyond the horrific nature of the cannibalism itself, what is most striking about this passage is that the woman’s complaint is not about the deprivations of the siege and the terrible lengths it drove her to, but of her neighbor’s dishonesty and deception at not keeping up her end of the child-devouring bargain.</p>
 <p style="body" n="58">While it is curious that an educated Jewish writer like Josephus would claim that Maria’s horrible deed was “of such a kind that has never been recorded by Greeks or barbarians, awful to tell and unbelievable to hear,” given the earlier story from 4 Kings 6:28, Chapman notes that in keeping with Josephus’s historiographical goals, making claims in his preface for the uniquely great nature of the Jewish war, it is important to omit an earlier Jewish example, the better to emphasize the unique awfulness of Maria’s desperate meal.<note target="#80" type="footnotelink">80</note> Thus, Jewish readers can recognize Josephus’s careful alignment with Hebrew scripture, apt for his contention that God’s wrath is responsible for the fall of Jerusalem because of the civil discord within. Meanwhile, for his Greco-Roman readers, this scene is a particularly vivid and grotesque example of a “stock scene” in siege narratives.</p>
 <p style="body" n="59">As Merrall Price has noted, this account of maternal cannibalism exists across the spectrum of fall-of-Jerusalem narratives; by the thirteenth century, the story was well-known enough as an exemplum of maternal depravity for Dante, Boccaccio, and perhaps even Chaucer to refer to it obliquely and assume their audiences’ familiarity with it.<note target="#81" type="footnotelink">81</note> However, <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> integrates several crucial changes. In earlier versions, such as that of Eusebius, the child cannibalized is a boy, which, combined with the mother’s name, Maria, suggests Eucharistic overtones.<note target="#82" type="footnotelink">82</note> By the time the narrative reaches the Vengeance of Our Lord tradition, however, new variants appear; in the French <hi rend="italic">Vengeance de</hi><hi rend="italic"> Nostre-Seigneur</hi>, Marie is not Jewish but an African Christian convert encouraged by her friend Clarice to cook and eat part of Clarice’s son, a deed Marie only agrees to upon urging by an angel, much like <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>’s narrative.<note target="#83" type="footnotelink">83</note> In this, <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> differs from <hi rend="italic">Siege</hi>, as well as Josephus, his Latin translation, Rufinus’s translation of Eusebius into Latin, and Pseudo-Hegesippus, all of whom omit Clarice and the exhorting angel. We would venture that the <hi rend="italic">Vengeance</hi> tradition, and <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>, perhaps see the reference to 4 Kings in the original account, and brings their story more in line with that story with the addition of Clarice. Combined with the prevalent mother-devouring-child imagery from other biblical sources (as in Jeremias and Kings), this version allows <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> to figure the downfall of Jerusalem as part of God’s divine plan, foretold in scripture.</p>
 <p style="body" n="60">Historical accounts of cannibalism during the First Crusade are pervasive, and Geraldine Heng has linked the narratives in chronicles of the period to medieval romance as a genre.<note target="#84" type="footnotelink">84</note> In her reading of the account in <hi rend="italic">Siege</hi>, Bonnie Millar notes that in eating her child, “[b]y breaking social taboos [Marie’s] actions convey the breakdown of social systems. This is something to which she has been driven by society.”<note target="#85" type="footnotelink">85</note> In making this action divinely approved, <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> sanctions the siege and the extreme conditions within the city of Jerusalem, fitting them neatly into God’s prophesied plan for the city’s downfall. Millar suggests that the narrative in <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> is simplified in several ways that fit the poem’s emphasis on horror, suggesting that in this episode, “[t]he emphasis is placed on the fact that Mary must do this against her will to fulfil the judgement decreed upon Jerusalem by God,” a necessary outcome of Marie’s Christian, rather than Jewish, background in <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>.<note target="#86" type="footnotelink">86</note></p>
 <p style="heading" n="6">Medieval English Antisemitism and Its Contexts</p>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="17">In part because of the broad network of sources it draws on, <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> has links to a variety of literary traditions circulating in medieval England. The scholarship on English anti-Judaic sentiment is substantial, and we cannot hope to examine it all here; nonetheless, an overview detailing the theological and historical situation of Jewish communities in relation to late medieval England contextualizes <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>’s treatment of its Jewish characters.<note target="#87" type="footnotelink">87</note></p>
 <p style="body" n="61">As many critics have observed, medieval Christians were aware that their own faith developed from and existed in opposition to Judaism: that is, Judaism was the necessary precursor to Christianity, yet its continued existence presented a challenge to notions of Christianity as universal. This tension led to particular vitriol leveled at Judaism and Jews in the literature and theology of the period as well as to violence against Jewish communities. As Geraldine Heng has recently suggested, “Jews functioned as the benchmark by which racial others were defined, measured, scaled, and assessed.”<note target="#88" type="footnotelink">88</note> This marginalized status was exacerbated by their proximity; while Muslims might occupy Jerusalem, Jews were to be found in communities across Europe. Their geographic position made Jews a convenient way for Christians to present alterity, thus endangering actual Jews. As Bale succinctly puts it, “medieval antisemitic representations allow us to see that which medieval Christians were not, or did not want to be.”<note target="#89" type="footnotelink">89</note></p>
 <p style="body" n="62">The position of Jews in medieval England was particularly fraught. Jews were essential to the developing English credit market, which made them uniquely endangered by Christian views of wealth and a target of resentment for anyone who needed financing; at the same time, they were imagined by Christians as ideologically subordinate, further justifying their murder and legal mistreatment. Though it is unclear whether Jews were originally linked to the English crown, they quickly came to be associated with royal authority, and in 1275, Edward I referred to English Jews as the king’s serfs, which made any rights and protections offered to Jewish communities subject to royal whim.<note target="#90" type="footnotelink">90</note> Scholars have noted that anti-Jewish sentiment resulted in legal action against Jews earlier in England than on much of the continent. England was the first European power to enforce the Fourth Lateran Council of 1215’s Canon 68, which required that Jews wear identifying markers on their clothing, with a law introduced by King Henry III on 30 March 1218.<note target="#91" type="footnotelink">91</note> Late twelfth-century England also saw multiple waves of violence against Jewish communities by Christians, notably in Lincoln (1189–90), York (1190), Bury St. Edmunds (1181),<note target="#92" type="footnotelink">92</note> Norwich (1144), and London (1276).<note target="#93" type="footnotelink">93</note> Of particular interest to readers of this poem, Jewish responses to violence wielded against them were sometimes linked to the 70 CE events at the fall of Jerusalem. As Anthony Bale explains, “William of Newburgh, the most eloquent Christian chronicler of the [1190 York] incident, reports that the leader of the York Jews, Rabbi Yom Tov of Joigny, modelled his speech and actions on those of the suicidal Zealots led by Eleazar at Masada (73 CE), as narrated by Josephus (c. 37–100 CE) in <hi rend="italic">De bello </hi><hi rend="italic">Judaico.</hi>”<note target="#94" type="footnotelink">94</note> The events surrounding the fall of Jerusalem held imaginative power for both Christians and Jews in the Middle Ages, serving as an affirmation of triumphant Christian violence and a model of Jewish resistance.<note target="#95" type="footnotelink">95</note></p>
 <p style="body" n="63">England was also the first European power to officially expel Jews, who were removed from the country by royal edict of Edward I in 1290.<note target="#96" type="footnotelink">96</note> As Bale notes, however, this seeming turning point had little to no impact on English antisemitism, which continued to thrive in England’s cultural products.<note target="#97" type="footnotelink">97</note> Spectral, virtual, though legally absent, Jews featured strongly in English cultural production, available for repeated marginalization in post-Expulsion literature by Christians.<note target="#98" type="footnotelink">98</note> Though <hi rend="italic">Destruction of Jerusalem</hi> long postdates official expulsion, it is one of many antisemitic literary texts that circulated in England in the later Middle Ages. Thus, <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> and works like it — including most famously Chaucer’s Prioress’s Tale but also the <hi rend="italic">Book of John Mandeville</hi>, Croxton <hi rend="italic">Play of </hi><hi rend="italic">the Sacrament</hi>, and others — continued to circulate and imaginatively shape notions of English identity.</p>
 <p style="body" n="64">These tensions rise to the surface especially in texts that focus on the city of Jerusalem. Jews are sometimes erased entirely from literary depictions of the city central to all three Abrahamic faiths imagined as displaced from the holy city;<note target="#99" type="footnotelink">99</note> at other times, they are strongly linked to Muslims, who had political control over the region for the vast majority of the later Middle Ages.<note target="#100" type="footnotelink">100</note> <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> resists both these urges, placing its Jews in Jerusalem — though a Jerusalem under Roman authority — and presenting them as a distinct community.<note target="#101" type="footnotelink">101</note> Narratives about Jerusalem served a devotional purpose, giving Christians the chance to engage in narrative travel as a kind of meditative exercise.<note target="#102" type="footnotelink">102</note> As Susanne Yeager has argued, Jews were both central to literary constructions of Jerusalem and considered a danger to the city. Roger Nicholson likewise notes that Jerusalem is central to notions of European Christendom in the same way as Troy narratives were crucial to developing ideas of national identity.<note target="#103" type="footnotelink">103</note> The poem’s crusading echoes are thus very much in keeping with its antisemitism, and these echoes extended beyond literary production. As Susanna A. Throop notes, the First and Second Crusades included attacks against Jews; she also describes a forged papal encyclical, allegedly by Pope Sergius IV (1009–1012), that claimed that Titus and Vespasian’s destruction of Jerusalem foreshadowed Crusading victory.<note target="#104" type="footnotelink">104</note> Thus, it is possible to read <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> alongside texts of the period that celebrate Crusading ideologies and imagine a successful reconquest of Jerusalem despite the poem’s first-century setting. These fantasies about Jerusalem hold particular sway in English contexts. As Yeager has suggested, “portrayals of Jerusalem articulated expressions of incipient national identity in late medieval England . . . English writings about travel to the holy city were part of a much larger project of constructing England in the image of Jerusalem.”<note target="#105" type="footnotelink">105</note> <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> follows in the same trajectory as English works such as <hi rend="italic">Richard Coer de Lion</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The Book of </hi><hi rend="italic">John Mandeville</hi>, or its counterpart text, <hi rend="italic">Siege of Jerusalem</hi>.<note target="#106" type="footnotelink">106</note> Thus, English identity and English antisemitism are entangled: <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>, in seeking to rid Jerusalem of Jews, fashions a literary expulsion for the Holy Land that mirrors the legal expulsion of Jews from England several hundred years before.</p>
 <p style="body" n="65">While the existing scholarly literature on <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> tracks its reinterpretations of Latin sources, the poem’s connections to medieval drama have been historically overlooked. These parallels make sense given <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> and the cycle plays’ shared interest in reproducing and translating Biblical narratives for vernacular audiences, as well as the shared source material; further, many of the Biblical stories reproduced in <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> also appear in English cycle plays. The episode of the woman taken in adultery, for example, appears in the York, N-Town, and Chester Plays. Diane Munro has identified several other passages that may well draw on the dramatic tradition, including the detail that Pilate’s wife’s dream came from Satan (present in Chester and N-Town Plays) and Mary’s presence at the ascension of Jesus (present in Wakefield and York Cycles).<note target="#107" type="footnotelink">107</note> Even the detailed violence with which the crucifixion is narrated and renarrated might be familiar from its dramatizations within the cycle plays; as Michael Livingston notes, the cycles included entire plays focused on the torture of Jesus.<note target="#108" type="footnotelink">108</note> Patricia A. DeMarco suggests that these depictions of the Passion are indeed designed to be traumatizing and that they are thus crucial to Christian identity formation.<note target="#109" type="footnotelink">109</note> Yet key to the use of Crucifixion narratives as a mechanism for Christian identity formation is its antisemitism: as Bale observes, “In popular religion, the Passion was reduced to a series of sensational and often crude moments of violence and degradation . . . In texts and images of the Passion we find the most violent and widespread antisemitic images, serving not only to represent Jews as the killers of Christ but also to vitiate and objectify the Jewish image more generally.”<note target="#110" type="footnotelink">110</note> While there is not an English dramatic version of the siege and destruction of Jerusalem, the narrative was dramatized on the continent, especially in French, as Steven Wright has discussed.<note target="#111" type="footnotelink">111</note> From its vernacularizing of Latin source material to its preservation in multiple versions across many manuscripts, <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> was clearly imagined for a wide and interested medieval English Christian public.</p>
 <p style="body" n="66">For <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>, the destruction of the temple is unequivocally the preordained consequence of Jewish condemnation of Jesus. In its retelling of Jesus’s lament over Jerusalem (lines 695–720), the poem narrates this account of the end times as a more focused, specific account of the city’s destruction by Roman siege.<note target="#112" type="footnotelink">112</note> Indeed, the poem is notable for its repeated assertions that readers should not pity the Jews because their suffering and justification is preordained vengeance.<note target="#113" type="footnotelink">113</note> These assertions are crucial to the poem’s antisemitism, serving as excuse and justification for its most violent passages.</p>
 <p style="heading" n="7">Manuscripts and Editions</p>
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="18">There are twelve manuscripts of <hi rend="italic">Destruction of Jerusalem</hi>.<note target="#114" type="footnotelink">114</note> While this fact alone is not necessarily proof of wide readership, the number of extant manuscripts is nonetheless noteworthy, particularly as <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> seems to survive in more copies than <hi rend="italic">Siege</hi> and many works are preserved in a single copy. The majority of manuscripts are of the somewhat unwieldy long version described above, although several of these are incomplete.</p>
 <p style="bodysubection">Long Version Manuscripts:</p>
 <list rend="bulleted">
 <item style="indent1"><hi rend="bold">A</hi>: London, British Library, MS Additional 36523, fols. 1r–71r<list rend="bulleted"><item style="indent2">Complete; second quarter of fifteenth century</item><item style="indent2">10 <hi rend="fraction">½</hi> by 7 inches</item></list></item>
 <item style="indent1"><hi rend="bold">L</hi>: Oxford, Bodleian, MS Laud Misc. 622, fols. 1r–21v, 71v–72v<list rend="bulleted"><item style="indent2">Complete: first 680 lines appear at end of MS; dated to around 1400</item><item style="indent2">11 <hi rend="fraction">¾</hi> by 10 <hi rend="fraction">¼</hi> inches</item></list></item>
 <item style="indent1"><hi rend="bold">C</hi>: London, British Library, MS Harley 4733, fols. 40v–127r<list rend="bulleted"><item style="indent2">Complete except a small gap, lines 4702–4730; around 1460</item><item style="indent2">8 by 5 inches</item></list></item>
 <item style="indent1"><hi rend="bold">D</hi>: Oxford, Bodleian, MS Digby 230, fols. 195r–223v<list rend="bulleted"><item style="indent2">Complete; middle of fifteenth century</item><item style="indent2">15 <hi rend="fraction">¾</hi> by 10 <hi rend="fraction">½</hi> inches</item></list></item>
 <item style="indent1"><hi rend="bold">O</hi>: New Haven, Beinecke Library, MS Osborn A.11,<note target="#115" type="footnotelink">115</note> fols. 1r–38v<list rend="bulleted"><item style="indent2">Partial: contains lines 1–4875, with a gap from lines 3719–75; early fifteenth century</item><item style="indent2">9 <hi rend="fraction">¾</hi> by 6 <hi rend="fraction">3/8</hi> inches</item></list></item>
 <item style="indent1"><hi rend="bold">Addit</hi>: London, British Library, MS Additional 36983, fols. 216r–255r<list rend="bulleted"><item style="indent2">Complete: however, lines 2201–2382 transposed with lines 3820–4002; circa 1440s </item><item style="indent2">11 <hi rend="fraction">¼</hi> by 8 <hi rend="fraction">½</hi> inches</item></list></item>
 <item style="indent1"><hi rend="bold">Douce</hi>: Oxford, Bodleian, MS Douce 126, fols. 69r–84r<list rend="bulleted"><item style="indent2">Partial: begins at line 3913 and continues to end; first half of fifteenth century</item><item style="indent2">9 by 6 <hi rend="fraction">½</hi> inches</item></list></item>
 <item style="indent1"><hi rend="bold">Douce 78</hi>: Oxford, Bodleian, MS Douce 78, fols. 19r–76v<list rend="bulleted"><item style="indent2">Partial: contains only the first 2295 lines; late fifteenth century</item><item style="indent2">8 <hi rend="fraction">¼</hi> by 5 <hi rend="fraction">¼</hi> inches</item></list></item>
 <item style="indent1"><hi rend="bold">Cov</hi>: Coventry, City Records Office MS 325/1,<note target="#116" type="footnotelink">116</note> fols. 98r–129v<list rend="bulleted"><item style="indent2">Partial: contains lines 80–5039; mid-fifteenth century</item><item style="indent2">12 <hi rend="fraction">2/3 </hi>by 7 <hi rend="fraction">½</hi> inches</item></list></item>
 </list>
 <p style="bodysubection">Short Version Manuscripts:</p>
 <list rend="bulleted">
 <item style="indent1"><hi rend="bold">P</hi>: Cambridge, Magdalene College, Cambridge University, MS Pepys 2014 (formerly Pepys 37), fols. 23r–35v <list rend="bulleted"><item style="indent2">Late fourteenth/early fifteenth century</item><item style="indent2">10 <hi rend="fraction">7/10</hi> by 7 <hi rend="fraction">1/5</hi> inches</item></list></item>
 <item style="indent1"><hi rend="bold">M</hi>: New York, Pierpont Morgan, MS M.898, fols. 1r–100r<list rend="bulleted"><item style="indent2">Fifteenth century</item><item style="indent2">5 <hi rend="fraction">5/8</hi> by 3 <hi rend="fraction">7/8</hi> inches</item></list></item>
 <item style="indent1"><hi rend="bold">B</hi>: London, British Library, MS Additional 10036, fols. 2r–61v<list rend="bulleted"><item style="indent2">Early fifteenth century (circa 1425)</item><item style="indent2">6 by 3 <hi rend="fraction">¾</hi> inches</item></list></item>
 </list>
 <p style="bodysubection">Previous Editions:</p>
 <list rend="bulleted">
 <item style="indent1">Fischer, Rudolf, ed. “<hi rend="italic">Vindicta Salvatoris</hi>.” <hi rend="italic">Archiv</hi><hi rend="italic"> für das Studium der neueren Sprachen und Literaturen</hi> 111 (1903), 285–98 and 112 (1904), 25–45. [using P as the base manuscript]</item>
 <item style="indent1">Herbert, J. A., ed. <hi rend="italic">Titus &amp; Vespasian: or The Destruction</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Jerusalem in Rhymed Couplets: Edited from the London and</hi><hi rend="italic"> Oxford MSS</hi>. London: Roxburghe Club, 1905. [using A as the base manuscript]</item>
 <item style="indent1">Munro, Diane A. “An Edition and Study of Portions of MS Laud Misc. 622 of the Bodleian Library.” Ph.D. Dissertation: Aberdeen University, 1977. [a partial edition of L that includes <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>]</item>
 <item style="indent1">Wilson, John Holmes, ed. “Titus and Vespasian: A Trial Edition of the Osborne Manuscript.” Ph.D. Dissertaton: Yale, 1967. [using O as the base manuscript]</item>
 </list>
 <p style="bodysubection">We have selected Bodleian Library MS Laud 622, abbreviated as L, as our base text. The earliest extant version of the poem, dated to around 1400,<note target="#117" type="footnotelink">117</note> the manuscript is in reasonably good condition, with some damage to the outer margins and several small holes.<note target="#118" type="footnotelink">118</note> Pricking and ruling is sometimes faintly visible, but not consistently so. <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> appears on folio 1r, but this is not the beginning of the poem. Folios 65–72 contain the first 680 lines of the poem, with two lines of the poem appearing as a single line of text; a <hi rend="italic">punctus</hi> indicates where the line break should be. Though these folios appear at the back of the manuscript, they contain the start of the poem; thus, the first line in the book is line 681, and the poem continues through folio 21v. As it appears from folio 1 to folio 21, the poem is copied in double columns, with blue capitals surrounded by rubrication. However, the early lines that appear on folios 65–72 are considerably more compressed: the poem is again written in two columns, but with couplets sharing a single line, and the margins are dramatically reduced.<note target="#119" type="footnotelink">119</note> We have compared L against all long version manuscripts of the poem, with major variants detailed in our textual notes.</p>
 <p style="body" n="67">Previous editions tend to be based on a single manuscript or else collate manuscripts from both the long and short versions of the poem. Phyllis Moe has argued that the short version of the poem should be privileged, largely because its narrative holds together more neatly without the digressions of the longer version.<note target="#120" type="footnotelink">120</note> It is certainly the case that that short version’s narrative is somewhat more coherent; however, given that the majority of manuscripts are of the long version, we have here chosen to edit the more frequently preserved version of the text. L is notable for the works alongside which <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> appears: Laud 622 also contains <hi rend="italic">Kyng Alisaunder</hi>, a life of Saint Alexis, Adam Davy’s visions of Edward III, a single-folio account of the Holy Land, and various biblically-inspired material, including “Fifteen Tokens before the Day of Judgment.”<note target="#121" type="footnotelink">121</note> As Nicole Clifton has suggested, then, the manuscript may serve as a sort of compendium of writings about the Middle East, broadly imagined.<note target="#122" type="footnotelink">122</note> Laud’s manuscript context emphasizes the extent to which the poem links current discourses of crusade, antisemitism, and pious violence. It also contextualizes the seemingly long prologue on Jesus’s Passion, making these lines part of its presentation of the geographic area’s history.</p>
 <p style="bodysubection">In our editorial practice, we have followed Middle English Texts Series guidelines as follows:</p>
 <list rend="bulleted">
 <item style="indent1">thorn (<hi rend="italic">Þ</hi>) has been modernized to <hi rend="italic">th</hi>;</item>
 <item style="indent1">yogh (<hi rend="italic">ȝ</hi>) has been modernized to <hi rend="italic">g</hi>, <hi rend="italic">gh</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">y</hi> as appropriate;</item>
 <item style="indent1">Middle English <hi rend="italic">the</hi> has been emended to either <hi rend="italic">the</hi> or <hi rend="italic">thee</hi> as sense demands;</item>
 <item style="indent1">we have normalized <hi rend="italic">u/v</hi> and <hi rend="italic">i/j</hi> to their modern spellings to facilitate reading.</item>
 </list>
 <p style="bodysubection">Punctuation is editorial. Several paraph markings appear in the margin of the text, which are noted in the Textual Notes. Breaks in the text indicate decorated capitals in the base manuscript, which are also recorded in the Textual Notes. </p>
 
 </div><div type="footnotes">
 
 <note type="footnote" n="1"><space rend="indent1"/>Moe, “A Study of Two Manuscripts,” p. 26; Herbert, <hi rend="italic">Titus and Vespasian</hi>, p. xliii.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="2"><space rend="indent1"/>“Affective Vengeance,” p. 331.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="3"><space rend="indent1"/>Only three of the manuscripts we consider here include any sort of title: L and A both call the poem “The Bataile of Jerusalem,” while O’s header, added by a later hand, reads “The vengeance of god taken upon the Jewys for Chrystus deathe.”</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="4"><space rend="indent1"/>For a more comprehensive account of these Early Modern versions, see Groves, <hi rend="italic">The Destruction of Jerusalem</hi><hi rend="italic"> in Early Modern English Literature</hi>. </note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="5"><space rend="indent1"/>See Moe, “A Study of Two Manuscripts,” for the most comprehensive discussion of differences between the versions. We follow Herbert and Wilson in privileging the long version of the poem.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="6"><space rend="indent1"/>We choose this wording to reflect the fact that while the Second Temple after the Babylonian exile was the foundation of the actual Temple destroyed in 70, Herod the Great almost completely replaced the Second Temple with his grandiose building projects in the 20s BCE. See Goldhill, <hi rend="italic">Temple</hi>, pp. 4–8.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="7"><space rend="indent1"/>Gospel passages, e.g. Mark 13:1–2, were cited as evidence of God’s plan.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="8"><space rend="indent1"/>Another example (important for our romance) is the Gospel of Nicodemus. See also Gatewood, “Narrative Characterization,” pp. 225–92 and Judd, “Pontius Pilate,” pp. 73–96.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="9"><space rend="indent1"/>See Josephus’s request for indulgence at <hi rend="italic">JW</hi> 1.9–12; and the destruction of the temple at <hi rend="italic">JW</hi> 6.249–280. All subsequent <hi rend="italic">JW</hi> citations will follow this book.section number format. </note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="10"><space rend="indent1"/>Steve Mason’s recent and magisterial <hi rend="italic">History of the Jewish War</hi> (hereafter, <hi rend="italic">HJW</hi>) should be the go-to reference for students of the Jewish War. Mason’s cogent analysis and reconstruction informs much of our summary below. The recent translation of Josephus by Martin Hammond and Martin Goodman in the Oxford World Classics series is an excellent accessible rendering of Josephus, with valuable notes and indices.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="11"><space rend="indent1"/>Josephus, <hi rend="italic">Jewish Antiquities</hi>, trans. Thackeray, Marcus, Wikgren, and Feldman, 14.112–13; all subsequent citations will follow this book.section number format. </note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="12"><space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Pro Flacco</hi> 67–69, trans. Macdonald. </note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="13"><space rend="indent1"/>On this see Barnes, “Sack of the Temple.”</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="14"><space rend="indent1"/>On the cultural contrast between Rome and Jerusalem in this period, see Goodman, <hi rend="italic">Rome and Jerusalem</hi>.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="15"><space rend="indent1"/>Interestingly, Judah Maccabeus was familiar to Christian audiences as one of the Nine Worthies, a group of figures seen as chivalric exemplars: three Christian, three pagan, and three Jewish. For a brief overview of the Nine Worthies, see van Anrooij, “Nine Worthies,” <hi rend="italic">Encyclopedia of the Medieval Chronicle</hi>, 2:1150–52.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="16"><space rend="indent1"/>Later, the emperor Claudius attempted to install Agrippa I as King of Judea, as a reward for Agrippa’s early support of Claudius’s succession of Caligula. However, Agrippa I died after only a few years, and Rome reinstalled its own people to take control of the region, deeming Agrippa II, his father’s heir, to be unready for rule. Agrippa II’s sister Berenice notoriously maintained a sexual liaison with Titus, the son of Vespasian, and emperor from 79–81 CE.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="17"><space rend="indent1"/>Tacitus, <hi rend="italic">Histories</hi> 5.3–9 is a representative example of Roman attitudes. </note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="18"><space rend="indent1"/>For an analysis of this elite group and its breakdown, see Goodman, <hi rend="italic">Ruling Class</hi>.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="19"><space rend="indent1"/>Mason, <hi rend="italic">HJW</hi>, pp. 365–70. Mason argues that a garrison commander at Sepphoris antagonized the locals and then deceptively chalked it up to recalcitrant rebels in the city.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="20"><space rend="indent1"/>This event happens in <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> as well, at lines 3911–15.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="21"><space rend="indent1"/>The cynic would of course note that since Josephus is writing his account of the war after the victory of Vespasian and Titus, it is all too easy (and convenient) to insert this <hi rend="italic">post facto</hi> “prophecy.”</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="22"><space rend="indent1"/>His second son, the later Emperor Domitian (ruled 81–96 CE), had been left behind in Rome.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="23"><space rend="indent1"/>Josephus counts out 12,000, which is likely an exaggeration.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="24"><space rend="indent1"/>The Menorah can still be seen on an interior panel of the arch of Titus. See Mason, <hi rend="italic">HJW</hi>, pp. 4–41, on the triumph and associated monuments.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="25"><space rend="indent1"/>There are references to a supposed earlier Aramaic edition in the preface to the <hi rend="italic">Jewish War</hi> (<hi rend="italic">JW</hi> 1.3), but there is no other evidence such an edition ever existed.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="26"><space rend="indent1"/>A further complication is that Josephus is our only real source of information about these sects.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="27"><space rend="indent1"/>Josephus, <hi rend="italic">Jewish Antiquities</hi> 18.12–15.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="28"><space rend="indent1"/>The “oral Torah” is teachings originally passed down over the generations. It was eventually written down after the destruction of the Second Temple. It is comprised of the Mishnah (the oral Torah itself) and the Gemara, a series of commentaries on the Mishnah. Together these two works comprise the Talmud, the preeminent text of Rabbinical Judaism.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="29"><space rend="indent1"/>While John does not appear in the <hi rend="italic">Destruction of Jerusalem</hi>, he does appear in its cognate text, the <hi rend="italic">Siege of Jerusalem</hi>. See <hi rend="italic">SJ</hi>, line 1137.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="30"><space rend="indent1"/>See <hi rend="italic">JW</hi> 3.340–55. </note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="31"><space rend="indent1"/>On the Roman triumph see Beard, <hi rend="italic">Roman Triumph</hi>.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="32"><space rend="indent1"/>Josephus, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, ed. Mason, 65.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="33"><space rend="indent1"/>Cotton and Eck, “Josephus’ Roman Audience.”</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="34"><space rend="indent1"/>The limitations on archaeology in Jerusalem, especially around the Temple Mount, mean that much of the additional evidence has been limited to Galilee. See Mason, <hi rend="italic">HJW</hi>, pp. 466–87 and for a recent survey. See Goldhill, <hi rend="italic">Temple</hi>, pp. 152–62 for a survey of the last major archaeological work on the Temple mount in the 1960s.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="35"><space rend="indent1"/>Josephus remarks on God’s vengeance in several places in the <hi rend="italic">JW</hi>, e.g. 2.539, 3.354, 4.104, 4.288–89, 5.19. Josephus adopts many of his ideas about civil discord from the work of Thucydides. See Mader, <hi rend="italic">Josephus and the Politics of Historiography</hi>.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="36"><space rend="indent1"/>E.g. <hi rend="italic">JW</hi> 2.390–94, 3.6, 3.293, 5.367–68, 6.38–41.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="37"><space rend="indent1"/>See Goodman, <hi rend="italic">Josephus’s Jewish War: A Biography</hi>, for a concise survey of the history of that text.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="38"><space rend="indent1"/>See Nisse, <hi rend="italic">Jacob’s Shipwreck</hi>, pp. 1–48 on the <hi rend="italic">Sefer Yosippon</hi>.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="39"><space rend="indent1"/>On the Greek manuscript transmission of the corpus, see Leoni, “Josephan Corpus.”</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="40"><space rend="indent1"/>Cassiodorus, <hi rend="italic">Institutions</hi>, p. 149. Some argue that Cassiodorus may have in mind here the work of Pseudo-Hegesippus, but since Cassiodorus explicitly refers to a work on the war in seven books (Pseudo-Hegesippus is only five books), it seems clear he is referring to a Latin translation of Josephus himself, not the adaptation of Pseudo-Hegesippus. Levenson and Martin, “Ancient Latin Translation,” p. 323 summarizes this debate.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="41"><space rend="indent1"/>In <hi rend="italic">Epistulae</hi> 71.5 Jerome claims he cannot translate the <hi rend="italic">Antiquities</hi> because the work is too long.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="42"><space rend="indent1"/>On Pseudo-Hegesippus, see Kletter, “Christian Reception,” p. 371.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="43"><space rend="indent1"/>Hence, for example, the canonical status of the pseudepigraphical letters of Paul. The Hippocratic corpus is also largely pseudepigraphical. Homer, Plato, and many ancient playwrights had many works attributed to them that, even in antiquity, were questioned. On Christian pseudepigraphical writings see Ehrman, <hi rend="italic">Forged</hi>. </note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="44"><space rend="indent1"/>The authorizing function of the figure of Josephus himself may partially explain his presence in our romance. Eusebius cites the authority of Josephus for his details on the destruction of Jerusalem in the <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical Histories</hi>, translated into Latin by the aforementioned Rufinus. This may also be one function of the <hi rend="italic">Testimonium Flavium</hi>, a brief passage about Jesus of Nazareth inserted into the text of Josephus’s <hi rend="italic">Jewish Antiquities</hi> 18.3.3. See Whealey, “<hi rend="italic">Testimonium Flavianum</hi>,” and Nisse, <hi rend="italic">Jacob’s Shipwreck</hi>, pp. 19–21.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="45"><space rend="indent1"/>On the Latin translations, see Levenson and Martin, “Ancient Latin Translation,” with a <hi rend="italic">cri de coeur</hi> for more work in this area. See too Schreckenberg, <hi rend="italic">Rezeptionsgeschichtliche</hi>, and more recently Kletter, “Christian Reception.” The only scholarly edition of Ps. Hegessipus is that of Ussani. A translation into English of limited utility by Wade Blocker is available at <ref target="http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/hegesippus_00_eintro.htm" type="external">http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/hegesippus_00_eintro.htm</ref>; but let the reader beware of the severe limitations and inaccuracies of this translation — a good translation remains a <hi rend="italic">desideratum</hi>.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="46"><space rend="indent1"/>We consider the poem a romance, though the issue of genre has also troubled editors of <hi rend="italic">Siege of Jerusalem</hi>. See Livingston’s Introduction (<hi rend="italic">SJ, </hi>pp. 14–15) as well as Nicholson’s discussion (“Haunted Itineraries,” pp. 452–54). Though not part of the alliterative tradition, <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> has a strong interest in reimagining historical events; likewise, its episodic structure and interest in recounting battles align it with the popular Middle English romance tradition. See Heng, <hi rend="italic">Empire of Magic</hi>, pp. 3–10, and Yeager, <hi rend="italic">Jerusalem in Medieval Narrative</hi>, pp. 11–15.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="47"><space rend="indent1"/>See Ford, <hi rend="italic">Vengeance</hi>, pp. 1–2.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="48"><space rend="indent1"/>Compare Gryting, <hi rend="italic">Venjance</hi>, pp. 6–22 and Ford, <hi rend="italic">Vengeance</hi>, pp. 27–35. These details are similarly absent from <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"> Siege of Jerusalem</hi>.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="49"><space rend="indent1"/>We track which portions of the text draw on which of these materials in the present edition’s Explanatory Notes. For an incredibly thorough account of the poem’s sources, see Munro, especially pp. 12–15.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="50"><space rend="indent1"/>For an edition of Roger d’Argenteuil, see Moe, <hi rend="italic">ME Prose Translation of Roger d’Argenteuil’s</hi><hi rend="italic"> Bible en francois</hi>. Higden’s <hi rend="italic">Polychronicon</hi> may well have been a source for the poem, as it retells a portion of Josephus’s and Pseudo-Hegesippus’s works and was very likely a source for <hi rend="italic">Siege of Jerusalem</hi> (Millar, <hi rend="italic">Siege and</hi><hi rend="italic"> Contexts</hi>, pp. 64–68.) Its inclusion in <hi rend="italic">Polychronicon</hi> is particularly interesting given that, as critics have observed, developing nationalism is one of <hi rend="italic">Polychronicon</hi>’s goals: see Bale, <hi rend="italic">The Jew in the</hi><hi rend="italic"> Medieval Book</hi>, pp. 44–47, for a brief discussion of the work’s agenda grounded in its manuscript contexts.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="51"><space rend="indent1"/>A. Boyarin, <hi rend="italic">Siege of Jerusalem</hi>, p. 21n2.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="52"><space rend="indent1"/>A. Boyarin, <hi rend="italic">Siege of </hi><hi rend="italic">Jerusalem</hi>, p. 18. For related arguments, see Narin van Court, “‘Siege of Jerusalem’ and Augustinian Historians,” pp. 228–29, and Mueller, “Corporal Terror,” pp. 287–89.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="53"><space rend="indent1"/>This deferred baptism may suggest a parallel to figures like Palomides in Malory’s <hi rend="italic">Morte d’Arthur</hi>, who has Christian beliefs but refuses baptism until he has fulfilled a quest that will prove his worthiness to be baptized.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="54"><space rend="indent1"/>See, for example, lines 3671–72.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="55"><space rend="indent1"/>Munro, pp. 105–06.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="56"><space rend="indent1"/>See, for example, Herzman, Drake, and Salisbury, <hi rend="italic">King Horn</hi>, lines 1393–94 and Laskaya and Salisbury, <hi rend="italic">Sir Gowther</hi>, lines 703–08.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="57"><space rend="indent1"/>The fifteenth century saw new methods of persecution for a heretical group known as the Lollards, who challenged the doctrine of transubstantiation and disapproved of pilgrimage and Biblical drama. It is perhaps not an accident, then, that some Middle English texts that reinforce the church’s sacramental authority, such as the short <hi rend="italic">St. Erkenwald</hi> and the Croxton <hi rend="italic">Play of the Sacrament</hi>, also appeared during this period. On the Lollards, see the work of Anne Hudson, especially <hi rend="italic">Lollards and Their Books and Premature Reformation</hi>; on the Croxton play in particular as a response to Lollardy, see Cutts, “An Anti-Lollard Piece,” where the argument originated.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="58"><space rend="indent1"/>Josephus <hi rend="italic">War</hi> 6.201–19. Compare Pseudo-Hegesippus, <hi rend="italic">Historiae</hi>, 5.40.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="59"><space rend="indent1"/>Josephus, <hi rend="italic">War</hi>, 6.214: Ταχέως δὲ καὶ Ῥωμαίοις διηγγέλθη τὸ πάθος. τῶν δ’ οἱ μὲν ἠπίστουν, οἱ δὲ ᾤκτειρον, τοὺς δὲ πολλοὺς εἰς μῖσος τοῦ ἔθνους σφοδρότερον συνέβη προελθεῖν [This suffering quickly was announced to the Romans. Some of them didn’t believe it, others were moved to pity, but it’s agreed that the majority of them came into more vehement hatred of the Jews.] (Translation by Mark J. B. Wright.) Compare Pseudo-Hegesippus, <hi rend="italic">Historiae</hi>, 5.41, with a more straightforward “pervenit etiam ad Romanos huius facti immanitas,” where only <hi rend="italic">immanitas</hi> conveys any sense of the response in the Roman camp, which Josephus makes explicit.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="60"><space rend="indent1"/>See Heng, <hi rend="italic">Empire of Magic</hi>. Heng argues throughout that symbolic cannibalism is a pervasive feature in medieval romance.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="61"><space rend="indent1"/>One exception to this trend is Tacitus, <hi rend="italic">Agricola</hi> 28, where a group of Usipii mutineers commandeer some ships and go marauding around Britain. As things increasingly do not go their way, the men are driven to at first eat the weakest among them, and then to eat others by drawing lots (<hi rend="italic">eo ad extremum inopiae venere, ut infirmissimos suorum, mox sorte ductos vescerentur</hi>). Finally, those left are captured and enslaved. For this strange episode see Ash, “Great Escape.”</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="62"><space rend="indent1"/>Herodotus, <hi rend="italic">The Persian Wars</hi> 4.106, trans. Godley.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="63"><space rend="indent1"/>Ammianus Marcellinus, <hi rend="italic">History</hi> 31.2.15, trans. Rolfe.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="64"><space rend="indent1"/>Herodotus, <hi rend="italic">The Persian Wars </hi>4.26, 3.38, trans. Godley. </note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="65"><space rend="indent1"/>Thucydides, <hi rend="italic">History of the Peloponnesian War </hi>2.70.1, trans. C. F. Smith.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="66"><space rend="indent1"/>Thucydides, <hi rend="italic">History of the Peloponnesian War </hi>3.82.2, trans. C. F. Smith.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="67"><space rend="indent1"/>Sallust, <hi rend="italic">Histories</hi> 3.61, ed. and trans. Ramsey (includes the odd detail that the Numantines took the time to salt the leftover meat from the cadavers for later use), Valerius Maximus, <hi rend="italic">Memorable Doings and Sayings</hi>, 7.6, ext. 2, ed. and trans. Shackleton; Appian, <hi rend="italic">Iberica</hi> 96, ed. and trans. McGing, and Florus, <hi rend="italic">Epitome</hi> 1.34.12, trans. Forster.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="68"><space rend="indent1"/>Appian, <hi rend="italic">Mithridates</hi> 38, ed. and trans. McGing.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="69"><space rend="indent1"/>Valerius Maximus, <hi rend="italic">Memorable Doings and Sayings</hi>, 7.6 ext. 3, ed. and trans. Shackleton.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="70"><space rend="indent1"/>ταχὺ δ’ἐξερρύη τὸ φιλότιμον αὐτοῦ καὶ φιλόνικον ἐν αἰσθήσει γενομένου τῶν ἀποριῶν, αἷς οἱ στρατιῶται συνείχοντο, καὶ τῶν ἀνθρωποφαγιῶν [but his ambition and contentiousness quickly flowed away when the deprivations of his soldiers came to his attention, even of the cannibalism.] (Plutarch, <hi rend="italic">Lucullus</hi> 11, ed. Ziegler and Gärtner, translation by Mark J. B. Wright.)</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="71"><space rend="indent1"/>Compare Appian’s disgust at <hi rend="italic">Iberica</hi> 96 ed. and trans. McGing at the conditions of the Numatines under siege, and Valerius Maximus’s condemnation of both the examples of Numantia and Calagurris (<hi rend="italic">Memorable Doings and Sayings</hi>, 7.6, ext. 2 and 3, ed. and trans. Shackleton).</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="72"><space rend="indent1"/>Caesar, <hi rend="italic">The Gallic War</hi> 7.77.13–14, trans. Edwards.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="73"><space rend="indent1"/>On Caesar and barbarians, see Mannetter, “Narratology in Caesar,” pp. 1–54; Barlow, “Noble Gauls”; Johnston, “Nostri and ‘The Other(s)’”; and Schadee, “Caesar the Ethnographer.”</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="74"><space rend="indent1"/>On this episode, see Chapman, “Josephus and the Cannibalism of Mary.”</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="75"><space rend="indent1"/>Most of the Roman elite had long been bilingual in Greek and Latin. In fact, the earliest Roman histories were written in Greek. See Feeney, <hi rend="italic">Beyond Greek</hi>, on the origins of Latin literature.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="76"><space rend="indent1"/>Josephus, <hi rend="italic">War</hi> 1.3: Ἑλλάδι γλώσσῃ μεταβαλὼν ἃ . . . τῇ πατρίῳ συντάξας. [By translating into the Greek language the things I had arranged before in my native language.] (Translation by Mark J. B. Wright.)</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="77"><space rend="indent1"/>Chapman, “Josephus and the Cannibalism of Mary,” pp. 420–21.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="78"><space rend="indent1"/>Most notably in the importance of stasis (civil discord) as a reason for Jerusalem’s fall to the Romans.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="79"><space rend="indent1"/>See too Deuteronomy 28:52–61, Lamentations 2:20, and Ezekiel 5:9–10.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="80"><space rend="indent1"/>Chapman, “Josephus and the Cannibalism of Mary,” p. 420.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="81"><space rend="indent1"/>Price, “Imperial Violence,” p. 278.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="82"><space rend="indent1"/>Price, “Imperial Violence,” pp. 276–78.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="83"><space rend="indent1"/>Price, “Imperial Violence,” p. 280.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="84"><space rend="indent1"/>Heng, <hi rend="italic">Empire</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Magic</hi>, pp. 23–43. Katherine Terrell has recently gathered relevant excerpts in translation for her edition of <hi rend="italic">Richard Coeur de</hi><hi rend="italic"> Lion</hi>; see Terrell, <hi rend="italic">Richard Coeur de Lion</hi>, pp. 227–34. For more extensive discussions, see also Rubenstein, “Cannibals and Crusaders,” and Tattersall, “Anthropophagi.” Millar, <hi rend="italic">Siege and Contexts</hi>, p. 103, suggests that the poet of <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> might have been influenced by Crusades accounts.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="85"><space rend="indent1"/>Millar, <hi rend="italic">Siege and Contexts</hi>, p. 91.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="86"><space rend="indent1"/>Millar, <hi rend="italic">Siege and Contexts</hi>, p. 102.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="87"><space rend="indent1"/>While this bibliography cannot be comprehensive, recent and seminal studies include Bale, <hi rend="italic">The Jew in the Medieval Book</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Feeling Persecuted</hi>; Lavezzo, <hi rend="italic">Accommodated Jew</hi>; Kruger, <hi rend="italic">Spectral Jew</hi>; Krummel, <hi rend="italic">Crafting Jewishness</hi>; Heng, <hi rend="italic">Invention </hi><hi rend="italic">of Race</hi>; Rubin, <hi rend="italic">Gentile Tales</hi>; Cohen, <hi rend="italic">Living Letters</hi>; D. Boyarin, <hi rend="italic">A </hi><hi rend="italic">Radical Jew</hi>; Delany, <hi rend="italic">Chaucer and the Jews</hi>; Tomasch, “Virtual Jew;” Mellinkoff, <hi rend="italic">Outcasts</hi>; Biddick, <hi rend="italic">Typological Imaginary</hi>; and Nisse, <hi rend="italic">Jacob’s </hi><hi rend="italic">Shipwreck</hi>. For an excellent, cogent, and brief description of the position of Jews in medieval England as it relates to texts in the Vengeance of Our Lord tradition, see A. Boyarin, <hi rend="italic">Siege </hi><hi rend="italic">of Jerusalem</hi>, pp. 15–18.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="88"><space rend="indent1"/>Heng, <hi rend="italic">Invention of Race</hi>, p. 55. Heng argues for the construction of Jewish identity as a racial identity in medieval England on the grounds of the particular, marginalized status of Jewish communities: see pp. 15–54, especially pp. 23–24 and pp. 27–31. As she asserts in <hi rend="italic">Invention of Race</hi>, p. 31, “In England, then, the Jewish badge, expulsion order, legislative enforcements, surveillance and segregation, ritualized iterations of homicidal fables, and the legal execution of Jews are constitutive acts in the consolidation of a community of Christian English . . . against a minority population <hi rend="italic">that has, on these </hi><hi rend="italic">historical occasions and through these institutions and practices, entered into </hi><hi rend="italic">race</hi>” (italics original).</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="89"><space rend="indent1"/>Bale, <hi rend="italic">The Jew in the Medieval </hi><hi rend="italic">Book</hi>, pp. 3, 5.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="90"><space rend="indent1"/>We draw on this summary from Heng’s recent work in <hi rend="italic">Invention of Race</hi>: see especially pp. 58–60 and pp. 65–67. For a more detailed and comprehensive treatment, see pp. 55–109.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="91"><space rend="indent1"/>Bale, <hi rend="italic">The Jew in the Medieval Book</hi>, p. 15; Heng, <hi rend="italic">Invention of Race</hi>, p. 15.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="92"><space rend="indent1"/>Bale, <hi rend="italic">The Jew</hi><hi rend="italic"> in the Medieval Book</hi>, p. 29, pp. 9–10.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="93"><space rend="indent1"/>Heng, <hi rend="italic">Invention of </hi><hi rend="italic">Race</hi>, p. 28. We are indebted to both Bale’s and Heng’s account of this history throughout this section.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="94"><space rend="indent1"/>Bale, <hi rend="italic">The Jew in the Medieval </hi><hi rend="italic">Book</hi>, p. 29.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="95"><space rend="indent1"/>For a comprehensive discussion of this event’s position as both, see Nisse, <hi rend="italic">Jacob’s Shipwreck</hi>, pp. 23–32.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="96"><space rend="indent1"/>Bale, <hi rend="italic">The Jew in the Medieval Book</hi>, p. 15. It is noteworthy that though Jewish communities began to return to the country under Oliver Cromwell, the edict of expulsion has never been formally revoked by the British crown. On Cromwell’s involvement in the readmission of Jews to England, see Endelman, <hi rend="italic">The Jews of Britain, 1656–2000</hi>, pp. 20–25.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="97"><space rend="indent1"/>Bale, <hi rend="italic">The Jew in the Medieval Book</hi>, p. 16.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="98"><space rend="indent1"/>We invoke here Kruger’s <hi rend="italic">Spectral Jew</hi> and Tomasch’s “Virtual Jew.”</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="99"><space rend="indent1"/>Akbari, <hi rend="italic">Idols in the East</hi>, p. 115–16.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="100"><space rend="indent1"/>Heng, “Romance of England,” pp. 142–50; see also Delany, “Chaucer’s Prioress, the Jews, and the Muslims,” pp. 44–45, on this connection.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="101"><space rend="indent1"/>While Muslims are often described as “Saracens” in literature of this period, here it is the Romans who are called Saracens (see lines 3671–72). Muslims are conspiciously missing from the poem, leaving Jerusalem’s Jews as the primary antagonists for Vespasian and Titus and their forces.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="102"><space rend="indent1"/>Yeager, <hi rend="italic">Jerusalem in Medieval Narrative</hi>, pp. 12–13.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="103"><space rend="indent1"/>Nicholson, “Haunted Itineraries,” p. 461.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="104"><space rend="indent1"/>Throop, <hi rend="italic">Crusading as an Act of Vengeance</hi>, pp. 45–46. </note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="105"><space rend="indent1"/>Yeager, <hi rend="italic">Jerusalem in Medieval Narrative</hi>, p. 15.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="106"><space rend="indent1"/>Yeager’s larger project compellingly argues that each of these works links territorial ownership, crusading discourses, and a growing sense of English national identity. See <hi rend="italic">Jerusalem in Medieval Narrative</hi>.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="107"><space rend="indent1"/>Munro, pp. 80, 103–04.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="108"><space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">SJ</hi>, p. 20, refers to Towneley Cycle plays 21 and 22; York Cycle plays 29 and 33; and Chester Cycle play 16 as examples.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="109"><space rend="indent1"/>DeMarco, “Cultural Trauma,” pp. 280–82.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="110"><space rend="indent1"/>Bale, <hi rend="italic">The Jew in the Medieval Book</hi>, p. 149. This binary is, unfortunately, still deployed; see for example Krummel’s “Staging Encounters” on Mel Gibson’s <hi rend="italic">Passion of the Christ</hi> and its connections to the York cycle plays.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="111"><space rend="indent1"/>Wright, <hi rend="italic">The Vengeance of Our Lord</hi>, pp. 1, 10.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="112"><space rend="indent1"/>This passage draws on Matthew 24 and Luke 21. </note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="113"><space rend="indent1"/>See for example lines 199–204, 275–84, 3509–18, and 3709–28.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="114"><space rend="indent1"/>For more comprehensive descriptions of these manuscripts, see Moe, “A Study of Two Manuscripts,” pp. 8–25; Herbert, <hi rend="italic">Titus and Vespasian</hi>, pp. xxvi –xli; Wilson, “Titus and Vespasian,” pp. i–iv; Munro, p. 2e–f; and Guddat-Figge, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, pp. 110–11. For comparison, <hi rend="italic">Siege</hi> exists in six complete and three additional fragmentary manuscripts; see A. Boyarin, <hi rend="italic">Siege of Jerusalem</hi>, p. 89, and Hanna and Lawton, <hi rend="italic">Siege</hi>, pp. xiii–xxvii.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="115"><space rend="indent1"/>We follow Herbert’s designations for manuscripts L, A, O, C, D, B, P, and M for the sake of consistency with existing scholarship. Abbreviations used for other manuscripts are our own.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="116"><space rend="indent1"/>This manuscript has been overlooked by much previous scholarship: it is not listed, for example, in Herbert’s edition, nor in <hi rend="italic">A New Index of Middle English Verse</hi> (entry 1881). Clifton, “<hi rend="italic">Alisaunder</hi> and Oxford,” p. 40, identifies it as a copy of <hi rend="italic">Destruction of Jerusalem</hi>, and we have identified it as a long version manuscript using a digital facsimile.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="117"><space rend="indent1"/>On this point, see Herbert, <hi rend="italic">Titus and Vespasian</hi>, pp. xxxv–xxxvii, as well as the Bodleian description at <ref target="https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_7410" type="external">https://medieval.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/catalog/manuscript_7410</ref>. Herbert suggests in his edition that L should be considered authoritative based on its dating, but opts to use A as his base text because it is a cleaner manuscript. However, in our view, the unusual binding should not disqualify L as base text, particularly given its interesting manuscript context.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="118"><space rend="indent1"/>See for example folios 4, 5, 20, 30.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="119"><space rend="indent1"/>Indeed, some of the words are obscured by the manuscript’s binding; see the Textual Notes.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="120"><space rend="indent1"/>Moe, “A Study of Two Manuscripts.”</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="121"><space rend="indent1"/>See Clifton, “<hi rend="italic">Alisaunder</hi> and Oxford,” pp. 40–41, for a discussion of the varied manuscript contexts of <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi>.</note>
 
 
 <note type="footnote" n="122"><space rend="indent1"/>Clifton, “<hi rend="italic">Alisaunder</hi> and Oxford,” p. 30. Charles Russell Stone, “Many Man,” p. 20, has likewise suggested that texts in Laud Misc. 622 demonstrate the “simultaneous influence of romance and history,” and this is in keeping with the poem’s other manuscript contexts. <hi rend="italic">Destruction</hi> appears with <hi rend="italic">The Book of John</hi><hi rend="italic"> Mandeville</hi> in Coventry, City Record Office MS 325/1, with religious verse such as the <hi rend="italic">Seven Penitential Psalms</hi> in A, and with works by Lydgate in Digby 230. Certainly, it differs considerably in form from <hi rend="italic">Siege</hi>, but like its alliterative counterpart, the poem is invested in historically-inspired events, like much medieval popular romance.</note>
 
 </div></body></text></TEI>
